<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A defence of the proceedings of the Right Reverend the visitor and fellows of Exeter College in Oxford with an answer to : 1. The case of Exeter College related and vindicated, 2. The account examin'd.</title>
            <author>Harrington, James, 1664-1693.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 131KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 31 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B23948</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11466917</idno>
  <idno type="VID">205037</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240880799</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing H830</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">11466917</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B23948)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 205037)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1463:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A defence of the proceedings of the Right Reverend the visitor and fellows of Exeter College in Oxford with an answer to : 1. The case of Exeter College related and vindicated, 2. The account examin'd.</title>
                  <author>Harrington, James, 1664-1693.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 48, [2], 3-8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Tho. Bennet ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1691]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect : pages cropped with loss of print.  Defective Union Theological Seminary Library copy spliced at end.</note>
                  <note>Text of the copy of the proceedings in Latin, with special t.p. and separate pagination.</note>
                  <note>Includes : "A copy of the proceedings of Dr. Master upon the Commission of Appeal" - [2], 8 p. at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Bury, Arthur, 1624-1713.</term>
               <term type="personal_name">Trelawny, Jonathan, --  Sir, 1650-1721.</term>
               <term type="corporate_name">University of Oxford.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">College administrators --  Legal status, laws, etc.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Canon law.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-04 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-04 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:205037:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:205037:1"/>
            <p>A DEFENCE OF THE PROCEEDINGS Of the Right Reverend The VISITOR AND FELLOWS of <hi>Exeter</hi> College IN OXFORD.</p>
            <p>With an ANSWER to
<list>
                  <item>1. <hi>The Case of</hi> EXETER <hi>College related and vindicated.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>The Account Examin'd.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Tho. Bennet</hi> at the Half-Moon in St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:205037:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:205037:2"/>
            <head>The PREFACE.</head>
            <p>THE Cause of the late <hi>Rector</hi> of <hi>Exeter</hi> hath been defended with as little <hi>Reason</hi> and as much <hi>Rudeness</hi> as it was at first carried on; and yet after all these <hi>Affronts</hi> and <hi>Indecencies,</hi> the <hi>Visitation</hi> of the <hi>Bishop</hi> of <hi>Exeter</hi> was not more legal in it self, than the <hi>Proceedings</hi> after it have been <hi>just and hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable.</hi> When the late <hi>Rector,</hi> upon the <hi>plain</hi> proof of <hi>scandalous</hi> Crimes had justly been expell'd, and his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moval wou'd have contributed to the <hi>quiet</hi> of the <hi>Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege,</hi> and to the <hi>peace</hi> and <hi>honor</hi> of the whole <hi>Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versity;</hi> the <hi>Visitor</hi> however declin'd the exercise of that power, which in those private Societies his <hi>Prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessors</hi> have always us'd, and depriv'd him of his <hi>Office,</hi> not of his <hi>Possession.</hi> Of all the <hi>Heads</hi> of <hi>Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leges</hi> that ever were in that <hi>University,</hi> Dr. <hi>Bury</hi> is undoubtedly the first, who, after the <hi>Visitor</hi>'s <hi>Sentence,</hi> enjoy'd the <hi>favour</hi> of an <hi>Ejectment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Some time after, as soon as the Bishop was inform'd that Dr. <hi>Bury</hi> expected <hi>Redress</hi> in the Courts of <hi>Westminster,</hi> He, upon his <hi>own</hi> motion, desir'd and obtain'd leave of waving his Privilege in the <hi>House</hi> of <hi>Lords.</hi> When afterwards the Cause depended before proper Judges in the Court of <hi>Kings-Bench,</hi> Mr. <hi>Painter,</hi> upon his Lordship's desire, endeavour'd to ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sten the Tryal, and the other pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ty, upon a <hi>just dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:205037:3"/>prevent it. These fair and honorable Procedures, which ought to have been <hi>prais'd</hi> and <hi>commended</hi> by an <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genuous</hi> Adversary, are nevertheless no <hi>fences</hi> against the <hi>malice</hi> of a <hi>weak</hi> and <hi>insolent</hi> Libel. The scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dals, coming from <hi>such</hi> hands, neither need nor deserve an Answer, especially since they are level'd against a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son who is <hi>much</hi> above the reach of those <hi>Calumnies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Interest,</hi> which the <hi>Visitor</hi> pursu'd, is already <hi>secur'd;</hi> the <hi>College</hi> which his <hi>Predecessors</hi> found<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, is, by him, reform'd; and that Society which in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect of the Tenets there publish'd, and the Enormities there committed, was the <hi>disgrace</hi> of the <hi>Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sity,</hi> is now a creditable <hi>Member</hi> at least, if not an <hi>Ornament</hi> to it.</p>
            <p>The Duty which the Bishop ow'd to the <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>University,</hi> is already successfully discharg'd; the <hi>care</hi> and <hi>preservation</hi> of both is now happily entrusted to other hands. The powers that he executed were lodg'd in him by his religious <hi>Predecessor;</hi> He, by appointment, is sole <hi>Patron</hi> and <hi>Conservator</hi> of that Society, and <hi>represents</hi> the <hi>Founder</hi> in his <hi>College,</hi> as well as succeeds him in his <hi>Diocess.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Heresie, Bribery,</hi> and other <hi>gross Immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralities,</hi> clearly prov'd upon the late <hi>Rector,</hi> occasi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on'd the <hi>Sentence,</hi> and after it the <hi>Censure,</hi> una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimously past by the <hi>whole University</hi> upon his <hi>bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sphemous</hi> Book, sufficiently confirms and justifies the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:205037:3"/>
            <head>A DEFENCE, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>MOST of those that have read the <hi>Case of</hi> Exeter <hi>Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege related and vindicated,</hi> are sufficiently convinc'd that so <hi>bad</hi> a <hi>Cause</hi> stood in need of <hi>better Advo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cates.</hi> The Pamphlet (as the Preface intimates) was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign'd to draw over the <hi>unthinking part of their Adversaries,</hi> and whatsoever influence it may possibly have had up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, it hath not fail'd of a contrary effect on the <hi>thinking part of their Friends.</hi> The only Art (if any) of the Discourse is, That it is intricate and confus'd, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexes the Cause which it cannot <hi>refute.</hi> And therefore the plain and direct Method of answering it, is to reduce the Controversie to a Point; and afterwards, in short, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider the <hi>wide</hi> and <hi>immaterial Exceptions</hi> to it.</p>
            <p>The single Point then now in Issue is, Whether Mr. <hi>Painter</hi> be <hi>Rector</hi> of <hi>Exeter College:</hi> His Admission must intitle him to that Office, and an Avoidance must preceed and war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant his Admission: If Dr. <hi>Bury</hi> then was rightly remov'd, there was room for a new Choice; And, since no other Objections are made, upon the lawfulness of his Expulsion the Validity of Mr. <hi>Painters</hi> Title depends. The most <hi>notorious Heresie, gross Incontinence,</hi> and <hi>scandalous Bribery,</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:205037:4"/>are admitted to be good Causes of Expulsion; but it is pretended that the <hi>Bishop</hi> of <hi>Exeter</hi> had no <hi>Conusance</hi> of the Cause, and consequently no Power of inflicting the <hi>Punishment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That the Bishop is <hi>Ordinary Visitor,</hi> and <hi>Patron</hi> of that College, is not to be deny'd, and that none else have any <hi>Visitatorial</hi> Power therein, is admitted: But a scruple is rais'd, whether, and how far this Power is subject to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strictions, when it is <hi>suspended,</hi> and how <hi>reviv'd:</hi> What are the imaginary Extent and Bounds; When the absence and return of this <hi>intermitting</hi> Authority.</p>
            <p>It is pretended then, that the Bishop of <hi>Exeter,</hi> tho <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Visitor</hi> of that College is barr'd from any Power of <hi>receiving</hi> Appeals, and is restrain'd from any other than a <hi>Quinquennial</hi> Visitation: And that therefore, upon the Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Appeal by Dr. <hi>Master</hi> within the <hi>Quinquennium,</hi> the Bishops Authority of making a Visitation is deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min'd.</p>
            <p>To prove this Opinion, two Assertions must be laid down.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>That the</hi> Visitor <hi>of</hi> Exeter <hi>College hath no Power of</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving Appeals.</item>
               <item>2. <hi>That the</hi> Execution <hi>of a</hi> Commission <hi>of</hi> Appeal, <hi>amounts to a</hi> Visitation.</item>
            </list>
            <p>For if the <hi>Visitor</hi> had <hi>both</hi> Powers lodg'd in him, it is not pretended that the Execution of <hi>one</hi> determines the <hi>other;</hi> and therefore <hi>their</hi> Cause depends on the Truth of <hi>both; ours</hi> on the Falsity of <hi>either</hi> of these Propositions.</p>
            <p>These Positions are so absurd in themselves, and so ill defended by the Promoters of them; that they are <hi>refuted</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:205037:4"/>as soon as <hi>explain'd;</hi> and the whole Controversie will va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish at the same time that the Terms are setled. It will not be immaterial therefore to discourse of the true meaning and extent of the Words <hi>Visitor, Ordinary, Appeal</hi> and <hi>Visitation,</hi> and from thence to discover the gross Errors and Mistakes of the late Pamphlet.</p>
            <p>And herein I must take leave to make use of not only the Authorities of <hi>Common Law,</hi> but in a great Measure to call in the Assistance of the <hi>Canon.</hi> For since the Statutes of Colleges have a necessary dependence on the <hi>Ecclesiastical Laws,</hi> since their Elections, Controversies, and Proceedings are regulated by <hi>them,</hi> since lastly Visitation it self, if it is not <hi>now</hi> always circumscrib'd to <hi>Spiritual Societies,</hi> was yet originally us'd in <hi>Churches</hi> only, and <hi>Religious Places</hi> and still pursues the usual Forms of the <hi>Canon Law;</hi> it it absolutely necessary, and is usual in the <hi>Year Books,</hi> in Cases of this Nature, to receive from the <hi>Canonists</hi> the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planation of those <hi>Terms</hi> which are borrow'd from them. And therefore tho the late <hi>Author</hi> hath been pleas'd to <hi>defie</hi> the <hi>Civil</hi> and <hi>Canon Law,</hi> yet all judicious and learned Men are satisfied, that as it is much easier to contemn any <hi>Science</hi> than to attain it; so in a Cause of <hi>Spiritual Conu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sance,</hi> or which is nearly allied thereto, it is much better to <hi>have Canon Law,</hi> than to <hi>want Common:</hi> For if we look into the late Case we shall find, that this sworn Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sary to <hi>Ecclesiastical Laws,</hi> took not his Malice against them out of any great propensity to <hi>Temporal;</hi> and that Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of <hi>one part</hi> of Learning is no certain pretence to <hi>another.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:205037:5"/>
            <p>A <hi>Visitor</hi> then who is in Law, always the <hi>Patron</hi> of a Society, and a <hi>Conservator</hi> of the <hi>Local Statutes</hi> thereof is intrusted by Law to reform all <hi>Abuses</hi> and <hi>Disorders</hi> therein, and to <hi>redress</hi> all <hi>Grievances</hi> of the Members thereof.</p>
            <p>The Appointment of this Person, who is to be <hi>Visitor,</hi> is the Act sometimes of the Law, and frequently of the <hi>Party:</hi> But when ever any Person by good Authority is made <hi>Visitor;</hi> the <hi>Law</hi> it self casts upon him all the <hi>Powers</hi> incident to, and necessary for the Discharge of that Office. A <hi>Visitor</hi> is a Term of as certain, and as determin'd, tho per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps not of so well known a Signification, as an <hi>Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor;</hi> and therefore tho the nomination of the Person him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self may be from the Party, the Authority is always <hi>ascer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd</hi> by <hi>Law,</hi> the one is <hi>ex Institutione,</hi> the other <hi>ex Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>visione Legis.</hi> And tho these Powers may be divided, and plac'd in several Persons, as <hi>Visitors, Ordinary</hi> and <hi>Extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary;</hi> yet where-ever any Person is constituted <hi>sole Visitor,</hi> and <hi>all others</hi> are expresly excluded; there the <hi>General Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment vests</hi> him with all Authority requisite to the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of his Duty. For if the Place be of necessity visi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, then the <hi>Rights</hi> of <hi>Visitation,</hi> where-ever they may be lodg'd, and to whomsoever transferr'd, cannot how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever be diminish'd, much less taken away. And therefore any <hi>discretionary Rules</hi> given to a Person who is confess'd to have the sole Authority of Visitation, ought to receive, espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially if they fairly can, such an Interpretation as is consistent with the known Powers of a <hi>Visitor,</hi> and the Will of the <hi>Founder.</hi> For whosoever by plain Words constitutes a <hi>Visitor,</hi> and afterwards is conceiv'd by doubtful Expressions to
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:205037:5"/>deprive him of the Power necessary for that Office, must either design to <hi>transfer</hi> this <hi>reserv'd Authority</hi> to some other, or for some time at least to <hi>exempt</hi> the Place from any <hi>Visitation.</hi> Now if the <hi>Exemption</hi> of such a Place from Visitation, for <hi>any</hi> time, upon any Grievance or Enormity committed, be repugnant to <hi>Law,</hi> and the letting in of another <hi>Visitor,</hi> be evidently contrary to the declard Will of the <hi>Founder;</hi> then it follows, that these restrictive Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections may and ought to be so construed, as may nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be repugnant to the <hi>Will</hi> of the <hi>Founder,</hi> nor deroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory to the <hi>known Law</hi> of <hi>the Land.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This <hi>General Power</hi> of <hi>Visitors,</hi> is not only (as will after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards appear) allow'd in all Books
<note place="bottom">a Fra. de Pav. de Vis. Marianus Soc. de Vis. Zerola. v. Vis. Mendo de Jure Acad. de Vis. Acad. Chopin. de Monast. &amp; de eorum Vis.</note> of <hi>Canon Law;</hi> but is likewise frequently in the <hi>Year Books,</hi> and other Reports of <hi>Common Law presum'd</hi> and <hi>acknowledg'd.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Littl. Sect.</hi> 139. <q>If they which hold their Tenements in <hi>Frankalmoign</hi> will not, or fail to do Divine Service; The Lord may not distrain, but may complain of this to their Ordinary or Visitor, praying him, that he will lay some <hi>Punishment</hi> and <hi>Correction;</hi>
               </q> for this, and also pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide, that such Negligence be no more done, and the <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary</hi> or <hi>Visitor</hi> of <hi>Right</hi> ought to do this: And <hi>Coke p.</hi> 96. Expounds of <hi>Right, de Droit,</hi> in the Right of his <hi>Office:</hi> And therefore that the Powers that belong to the Office of a Visitor, are such as can correct at any time <hi>all Failures</hi> and <hi>redress them.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:205037:6"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Term. Mich.</hi> 9. <hi>H.</hi> 6. <hi>fol.</hi> 34 &amp; 33. The Visitor, or Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Paramount of the Order, hath power to visit an <hi>Abby,</hi> and those Powers are declar'd to be General, <hi>Ordinary</hi> and <hi>Extraordinary.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And therefore by the Statute 2 <hi>H.</hi> 5.1. Visitors are ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to enquire into the <hi>Governance</hi> and <hi>State</hi> of <hi>Hospitals, &amp;c.</hi> and of <hi>all other Matters</hi> (without restriction of Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences or limitation of time) and <hi>to reform,</hi> and <hi>to cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect them:</hi> and in the Case of <hi>Sutton</hi>'s <hi>Hosp.</hi> 10. Rep. p. 5. To visit, is explain'd by, to <hi>order</hi> and <hi>reform all Disorders and Abuses</hi> in and touching the said Hospital.
<note place="bottom">a
<p>See <hi>Siderf.</hi> p. 71. <hi>Widrington's</hi> Case, <hi>and</hi> 8 <hi>Ass. Ed.</hi> 3.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>P.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 1. <hi>Ordinary.</hi> See <hi>Minard Pictav. Antecessor ad Cap. Conq. de Officio Jud. Ord. Ordinary ad le Power de Visitation de</hi> Me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o Jure <hi>Dav. Rep. p.</hi> 3. See <hi>Mendo de jure Acad. Ad Ordinarium spectat Universitas Causarum Calv. in v. Ord.</hi>
                  </p>
               </note>
               <hi>Visitator est fidei Commissarius,</hi> is the Trustee and Representative of the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and hath the same Power in the <hi>Government</hi> and <hi>Preser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation</hi> of the College, as the Founder himself; and therefore it is evident, that in both <hi>Laws</hi> the <hi>Universal Jurisdiction</hi> of all Causes relating to the <hi>State</hi> of the Society, and the <hi>Governance</hi> thereof is of <hi>Right,</hi> and of <hi>necessity</hi> committed to the Visitor.</p>
            <p>Now if this Rule holds in the Case of a Visitor in General, it is infinitely more strong for him, who is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stituted <hi>Ordinary,</hi> or <hi>Ordinary Visitor;</hi> For that Word, as well in Canon, as in Civil Law, (and since, as thence receiv'd) in <hi>Common,</hi> implies and carries with it <hi>origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal</hi> and <hi>universal</hi> Jurisdiction. An Ordinary is distinguish'd as from a <hi>Delegated;</hi> so from a <hi>restrain'd</hi> Judge, he hath within his <hi>Sphere,</hi> and within his <hi>Forum</hi> (whether Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, Ecclesiastical or mixt) the Conusance of all Causes
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:205037:6"/>whatsoever, and that of himself, without any <hi>deputation.</hi> And therefore tho the <hi>Nature</hi> of the Causes, and the <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedure</hi> upon them may be different; yet as to the <hi>rise</hi> and <hi>extent</hi> of the Power, the Jurisdiction of all Ordinaries in their respective Courts, must be the <hi>same,</hi> and equally <hi>Universal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now then as the <hi>Canon</hi> for prevention of Proxies re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strains the Bishop, tho <hi>Ordinary</hi> to <hi>triennial Visitations</hi> of his <hi>Diocess;</hi> so the Local Statutes for prevention of <hi>Spor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulage,</hi> limit Visitors to a <hi>Quinquennial</hi> Visitation of their Colleges: And yet the Canon, and the Statutes that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strain the Solemn Visitation, bar them not in the mean time from the ordinary <hi>Acts of Jurisdiction.</hi> A general and chargable Enquiry <hi>ex Officio mero</hi> into Matters undetected is limited; but a redress of <hi>emergent</hi> Grievances, and the Conusance of Matters delated, as necessarily incident to his Office of <hi>Ordinary,</hi> neither is, nor without an apparent Failure of Justice can be <hi>taken away,</hi> or <hi>restrain'd.</hi> And therefore as in all Dioceses, so in all <hi>Colleges,</hi> where the Right of a <hi>triennial</hi> or <hi>quinquennial</hi> Visitation is lodg'd, there in the same Person, this <hi>Power</hi> of redressing Grievances in the interval, hath always been <hi>presum'd</hi> and <hi>allow'd.</hi> And as the <hi>Practice</hi> in all <hi>Colleges</hi> hath always been the same, so is the reason of it too: An <hi>Universal Provision</hi> for all Grievances is design'd; the Redress of them is plac'd in the Ordinaries and Visitors only; and therefore their Power doth
<note place="bottom">
                  <p>
                     <hi>Visitatio intromittitur saepius necessitate existente, Ugolin p.</hi> 103.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Regula quae respicit Commune, &amp; regularem visitationem, quae fit etiam fine causit, non prohibet iteratam, si causa subesse. Marian. Socin. de Vis.</hi> See <hi>p.</hi> 241.</p>
                  <p>This <hi>Fra. de Pavinis</hi> calls <hi>quotidiana Visitatio, quae fit quotidie ex multis causis eme gentibus. Tr. Tract. Tom.</hi> 14.</p>
               </note>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:205037:7"/>and must during the <hi>triennial Term</hi> extend it self to any oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casional Exorbitances. It is further observable, that an Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary is said to have an <hi>internal Jurisdiction,</hi> and such an one as is opposite to a forreign Authority; and therefore when Bishops visit their own Hospitals <hi>de Jure,</hi> they act as <hi>Ordinaries,</hi> but when appointed by the King, they have only a <hi>borrow'd, forreign,</hi> and <hi>delegated</hi> Jurisdiction. When Bishops visited their Dioceses, they were <hi>domestick</hi> Judges; but when <hi>tanquam Sedis Apostolicae delegati,</hi> they visi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Monasteries and places exempt; they had only an <hi>extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary</hi> and <hi>derivative</hi> Authority.</p>
            <p>This is the Power of a Visitor, which may and ought to be exercis'd in those Places that are of right visitable, and therefore it is next to be remark'd, that not only <hi>Churches,</hi> but all <hi>Free Chappels,</hi> all
<note place="bottom">a <hi>Coke</hi> 10. <hi>Sut. Hosp.</hi> 31. <hi>Brook Ab.</hi> 55. <hi>vid.</hi> 2. <hi>H.</hi> V. <hi>St.</hi> 1. 14 <hi>Eliz. c.</hi> 5. 13 <hi>Eliz. c.</hi> 17. <hi>Lyndw. l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 10. 14 <hi>Eliz. c.</hi> 5. 2 <hi>Inst.</hi> p. 725. <hi>Roll's, Ab. f.</hi> 229. 8 <hi>E.</hi> III. 70.37. <hi>Davies Proxies</hi> 23. 9 <hi>H.</hi> VI. 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 9 <hi>Ed.</hi> IV. 24.</note>
               <hi>Hospitals</hi> and <hi>religious Houses,</hi> as well of <hi>Seculars</hi> as <hi>Regulars,</hi> all <hi>Universities</hi> and <hi>Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leges,</hi> all
<note place="bottom">b
<p>See <hi>Hostienfis de Rel. Dom.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Greg. l.</hi> 5. <hi>Tit.</hi> 31. <hi>c. nimis iniqua. Quarrant v. Exempt. Genuens. in prax, c.</hi> 59. <hi>Vid. Rebuff. de confra. Lup. de Xen. Summa Sylvest. in v. Hosp.</hi> § 2. <hi>n.</hi> 3. <hi>Rolls. Ab. p.</hi> 22<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, 230.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Vgotin. p.</hi> 103. <hi>Visitari debent ab Episcopis quae Generalibus Capitulis non sunt subjecta.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Angel. in v. Hospit. <hi>Et hoc procedit etiamsi Testator qui aedificavit prohibuisset; ne Episcopus in tali negotio intromitteret Conc. Trid. Sess.</hi> 7. <hi>c. quia Testator non potest facere, quin in leges suo Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stamento locum habeant.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>11 <hi>H.</hi> IV. <hi>&amp;</hi> 41. <hi>Ed.</hi> III. 5, 6. See <hi>Marrad. de Jure Abbatum Praescriptio tollens visitationem non valet, quia cedit in damnum publicum, sed valet quae transfert.</hi>
                  </p>
               </note>
               <hi>Lay-Confraternities</hi> instituted for <hi>charitable De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signs,</hi> and in <hi>short,</hi> all <hi>Loca pia,</hi> whether they be <hi>ecclesia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stical, lay,</hi> or <hi>mixt Societies,</hi> are in both Laws, Canon and Common, subject to Visitation. And therefore if no parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Visitor be appointed by the Founder, and no other provision is by Law made for the Visitation, then the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:205037:7"/>and Statute supply the Omission, and entrust the <hi>Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary of the Place</hi> with this universal Jurisdiction. There is no prescription against Proxies, no more than against Tiths; the one is as incident to a Visitation as the other to Instruction; and both those are and have been esteemed of indispensible necessity. Visitation is as incident to those Societies as a <hi>Court</hi> to a <hi>Mannor,</hi> and is equally of common <hi>right</hi> and of common <hi>necessity:</hi> And therefore
<note place="bottom">b <hi>Non valet praescriptio ut ab aliquo visitari quis non possit, sed bene valet contra Episcopum quod alius Praelatus visitet.</hi> Cald. Lond. 453.</note> it is, and was a received Rule in both Laws, that of such visitable Places and Persons none can in any place be wholly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empt, but must either be immediately <hi>subject</hi> to one, or <hi>reserv'd</hi> to another Power.</p>
            <p>Now there are two <hi>Methods</hi> by which all Grievances and all Exorbitances may be brought into question before the Visi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor; one is the Complaint of the Party aggriev'd; the other the <hi>general Enquiry</hi> of the Visitor himself into all the Offences of his Subjects: The former is by the <hi>Prosecution</hi> of the Party, the latter upon the <hi>mere Office</hi> of the <hi>Judg;</hi> the one of these, tending to the Redress of particular and occasional Grievances, gives foundation to an <hi>Appeal;</hi> the other, aiming at the Reformation of all general growing Misdemeanours and Exorbitances, affords Matter for a <hi>Visitation.</hi> Now tho it is certain that all Visitors are entrusted with both these Powers, as equally necessary for the preserving the College, yet is it no less evident, that both these are distinct in their <hi>Nature and End;</hi> and that nothing but gross Ignorance can confound them. Nothing but Complaint made to a supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior
<note place="bottom">a Dav. Rep. Case Proxies.</note>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:205037:8"/>
               <hi>Judg</hi> by a <hi>particular</hi> Person, in his own necessary <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence</hi> for his own <hi>private Interest,</hi> and which tends not so much to the <hi>Punishment</hi> of <hi>Offenders,</hi> as to his <hi>own Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief,</hi> can produce and occasion a Commission of <hi>Appeal.</hi> But the Confession of his own Subjects, made upon Oath to a <hi>Judg,</hi> upon his <hi>enquiry</hi> for the <hi>Execution of Justice</hi> and which propounds not any <hi>private</hi> Amends and Satisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, but the <hi>publick Good,</hi> and the <hi>Safety</hi> of the <hi>Body Corporate</hi> is the ground of a <hi>Visitation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now then, since I have in short laid down the necessary Powers of a <hi>Visitor</hi> and an <hi>Ordinary;</hi> the usual <hi>Methods</hi> of their Procedure upon an <hi>Appeal,</hi> and in a <hi>Visitation;</hi> and lastly have shown the <hi>Nature</hi> of Places <hi>visitable;</hi> it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains as briefly to apply these certain and general Rules to the present Case in question.</p>
            <p>The Founders of Colleges then as they design the Perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuity of their Estate, so they equally desire the Continuance of their own Laws and local Statutes.
<note place="bottom">a 6 <hi>H</hi> VII. 14. <hi>Fitz. N. Br. fol.</hi> 93 94.</note> Their Trustees for enforcing these Orders and Constitutions are by Law their <hi>Heirs;</hi> and, by appointment, usually among Bishops, their <hi>Successors.</hi> These are, in respect of their Protection of the College, called <hi>Patrons;</hi> in reference to their Jurisdiction, <hi>Visitors.</hi> For as it is a certain Rule, That a Founder hath in him the Power of <hi>Visitation,</hi> so is it no less controverted, that a
<note place="bottom">b 8 <hi>E.</hi> III. <hi>Ass.</hi> 29. <hi>&amp;</hi> 250.</note> Patron, who is <hi>loco Fundatoris,</hi> succeeds to those Rights, and by construction of Law, is <hi>Visitor.</hi> Oftentimes, as is easie to be seen in the Charter of ancient Hospitals and religious Societies; there is nothing more specifi'd than <hi>Visi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatorem
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:205037:8"/>relinquimus;</hi> and in others, <hi>Patronum designamus;</hi> and those words only by plain and necessary implication, convey'd the visitatorial Jurisdiction in its full extent and latitude. The Power of receiving Appeals was so great and so necessary a part of that Authority, that tho I find in very few Statutes of Monasteries and religious Societies, that Liberty expresly given them, yet was it <hi>presum'd, own'd</hi> and <hi>practis'd</hi> in all. Whether the <hi>visitatorial</hi> Power was lodg'd in the <hi>Ordinary</hi> of the place, the <hi>Principal</hi> of the Order, the <hi>superior Abbot,</hi> the <hi>Capita Ordinum,</hi> the <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dex Academicus,</hi> the <hi>Conservator Universitatis,</hi> or lastly in the <hi>local Visitor</hi> of the College, it is a certain undeniable Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sition, that wherever the entire Power of <hi>Visitor</hi> is plac'd in one Person, there, as an <hi>incident</hi> to the Office, the Redress of Grievances upon Appeals was by Law vested and setled.</p>
            <p>And therefore, tho the pretended Restrictions are as strong in almost all Colleges in the University as in <hi>Exeter,</hi> there is not one, at least of any standing, wherein Appeals have not constantly been made to the <hi>Visitor.</hi> And as Custom and common Practice have own'd the <hi>Visitor</hi>'s Authority herein, so likewise the Courts at <hi>Westminster</hi> have counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanc'd and approv'd it. And therefore in <hi>Apleford</hi>'s Case, <hi>Mic.</hi> 22. <hi>Car. B. R.</hi> in <hi>Widrington</hi>'s Case, <hi>Hill.</hi> 13. and 14. <hi>Car.</hi> II. <hi>B. R.</hi> in
<note place="bottom">c See <hi>VVhitlock</hi>'s <hi>Read, Div.</hi> 3. <hi>Point</hi> 9. See <hi>Patrick</hi>'s Case, <hi>Hill.</hi> 18, 19. <hi>Car.</hi> II. <hi>B.R.</hi>
               </note> Dr. <hi>Lewis</hi>'s Case, Provost of <hi>Oriel.</hi> in <hi>Parkinson</hi>'s Case, 1<seg rend="sup">mo</seg> W. <hi>&amp;</hi> M. <hi>B.R.</hi> in <hi>Proost</hi>'s Case, <hi>Hill.</hi> 3<seg rend="sup">io</seg> W. <hi>&amp;</hi> M. <hi>B.R.</hi> it is resolv'd, That the proper Remedy of all ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell'd or injur'd Heads Fellows or Members of Colleges, lies in an Appeal to the local <hi>Visitor</hi> only, and that they are conclud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:205037:9"/>by this determination. <q>If there be a Jurisdiction in the <hi>Visitor,</hi> saith my Lord C. J. <hi>Hales,</hi> and he hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termin'd the Matter, how will you get over that Sentence? and thereupon a <hi>Mandamus</hi> was deny'd.</q> But if a Fellow had no Visitor to whom he might appeal, as in <hi>Herns</hi> Case, the <hi>Mandamus</hi> was granted and adjudg'd good. Since there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in all other Societies and Monasteries an Appeal to the <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sitor</hi> hath been granted, since in all Colleges it hath been us'd and allow'd, and since as in all foreign <hi>Courts,</hi> so especially in those of <hi>Westminster</hi> it hath been unquestionably admitted, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing needs further to be added to the Confirmation of it, than that in <hi>Exet,</hi> Coll. the Statutes do more plainly cast that Power upon the <hi>Visitor,</hi> than in most other Colleges of the University.</p>
            <p>The Statute <hi>De Visit.</hi> says, <hi>Adeo pronum &amp; ad malum pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clive est humanum genus, &amp; uti quotidie videmus, varietas tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porum optima quaeque aufert, &amp; mutat, ut non sit in nostrâ po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testate eas condere Leges &amp; Statuta quae non violet aliquan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do astutus, &amp; versipellis, aut malè interpretando aut aliquid fraudis ingerendo aut excogitando modum quo nodum quamvis Herculeum dissolvat.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Distinctions,</hi> he was sensible, were to be found out; the Statute might easily be eluded; <hi>Bribery</hi> might be construed <hi>Repairs; Promotionis causa</hi> might be interpreted a Benefice, and therefore against all these Evils he provides a <hi>Visitor,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happily not forefeeing, that even this Remedy it self might <hi>malè interpretando</hi> be distinguish'd into <hi>nothing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Nos eam ob causam, ea quae duximus nostro tempore utilia &amp; commoda, inferentes quòd ea conservanda rectéque interpretanda attinet, confidimus authoritati &amp; benignitati Episcoporum</hi> Exoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ensium <hi>Successorum nostrorum, quos dicti Coll. Patronos &amp; Visi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatores
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:205037:9"/>relinquimus, ut illi qui ex sua liberalitate &amp; mera benignitate adducti ac fervidâ charitate in fidem Christianam inflammati, ad hoc Alvearium conservandum invigilent, ut Statuta &amp; Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiones dicti Collegii firmiter observentur, virtutes &amp; disciplinae nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triantur possessiones &amp; bona spiritualia &amp; temporalia prospero statu floreant, jura, libertates &amp; privilegia defendantur &amp; protegantur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now I would willingly know, whether <hi>relinquimus Patronos, &amp; Visitatores,</hi> be <hi>operative</hi> Words or not; whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>confidimus autoritati &amp; benignitati Episcoporum</hi> Exo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niensium <hi>ut ad hoc</hi> Alvearium <hi>conservandum</hi> invigilent <hi>ut Statuta &amp; Ordinationes dicti Collegii firmiter observentur, &amp;c.</hi> are fit for an universal provision; and do consequently lodge in the Visitors thereof an <hi>Universal Jurisdiction?</hi> whether it is possible to defend <hi>Possessiones &amp; bona spiritualia &amp; temporalia</hi> by a Visitation once in <hi>Five</hi> Years, which may be dilapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dated in less than <hi>one;</hi> whether it will be easie <hi>protegere Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra &amp; Libertates</hi> of the Members thereof, by restoring them Five Years after Expulsion? Could there be more expres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sive, plain and extensive Words found out for the Settlement of the Visitatorial Power? and can it afterwards be thought that the Founder design'd to expose his College and the Members thereof to all <hi>growing Evils,</hi> to all <hi>occasional Grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances,</hi> and <hi>emergent Exorbitances</hi> and <hi>Combinations?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is plain then that the Founder repos'd the whole Trust and Care of the College in the B. of <hi>Exeter</hi> his Successor; and to that end constituted him <hi>Ordinary Visitor,</hi> and <hi>Patron</hi> thereof, in so general and expressive Words, that in all the Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointments of the <hi>Visitors,</hi> either of Hospitals or of Monasteries, or of Colleges; I never saw, and believe there is not, any one Instance wherein larger Powers were granted to a Man, and
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:205037:10"/>where the Grant was ever made with more Solemnity: And therefore, if this Power (which is an impossible Supposal); but if it should fail in its bottom, I dare, upon enquiry, affirm, that <hi>no visitatorial Jurisdiction</hi> of <hi>Churches, Hospitals</hi> and <hi>Chappels,</hi> can upon more expressive Words be main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd and supported, and that all the provisonary Consti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions of those Societies were vain and idle Appointments. For if Founders do adjure, and in <hi>Visceribus Jesu Christi</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seech their Successors; <hi>ut fervidâ Charitate</hi> in <hi>fidem Christia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam inflammati,</hi> they should expell all Heresie from their So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety; and if afterwards their <hi>Saviour</hi> in this very College should be expos'd as a <hi>Galilaean</hi> Vagabond, and a <hi>Crucifi'd</hi> Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gabond, and if all the Fundamentals and Articles of Faith should be therein ridicul'd to the known disturbance and abhorrence of the whole University in a most solemn manner dclar'd; and if, lastly, it is impossible for the sole Visitor of that College to give any redress herein, or to allow any less scope to the Rector for Libelling his Saviour here then a <hi>Quinquennium;</hi> then it must be allow'd, I suppose, that these Rules and Orders were inconsistent and null, and the well meant Dreams of their <hi>Religious Founders;</hi> But if an Universa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of Jurisdiction, as plainly it is, be lodg'd in the Bishop, and may upon such Emergencies be exerted, then is the Founder consistent with himself, then his plain Words will have their due Force; And the College according to his ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment may be govern'd and preserv'd.</p>
            <p>I shall insist now on no more than one other Branch of the Statute. <hi>Quos</hi> quidem <hi>Rectorem Subrectorem, &amp; Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctos, ac praeterea Ministros quoscun{que} &amp; Famulos, praedicto</hi> Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mino
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:205037:10"/>Episcopo, <hi>&amp; suo</hi> Commissario, <hi>sed nulli alli, volu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus &amp; praecipimus effectualiter intendere &amp; parere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As before, the Bishop was appointed Visitor; so here all others are barr'd from any Partnership in the Authority: The Powers that were given him are <hi>intire,</hi> and <hi>undivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded;</hi> and all the Controversies are taken away, that usual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly arise from <hi>concurrent</hi> and <hi>interfering</hi> Jurisdictions.</p>
            <p>Now since by express Words so large Authority is plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly lodg'd in the Bishop of <hi>Exeter;</hi> let us consider what is offer'd to divest him of this Power.</p>
            <p n="1">1. A Fellow hath sworn not to commence a Suit against the College, and hath renounc'd the Right of Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealing.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Omni Actioni contra Rectorem, &amp;c. quomodolibet appellationi &amp; querelae in ea parte faciendis &amp; quarumcun{que} literarum im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petrationi, precibus principum, praelatorum, &amp;c. quibus possem ad jus, titulum &amp; possessionem vendicandam reconciliari, ac quibuslibet juris vel facti remediis, per quae me petere possem in integrum restitui, quantumcun{que} aliàs mihi probitatis &amp; vitae merita suffra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gantur in vim pacti renuncio.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now if in this Oath it should be admitted that the <hi>general Words</hi> should include the <hi>Visitor,</hi> as they plainly do not; yet nevertheless how can any Judge be <hi>sworn out</hi> of his Authority by a Fellow? If he had not Power of receiving Appeals before, The Oath under this Interpretation would be <hi>vain;</hi> and if he had, the Oath, in regard of the Visitor would be <hi>void</hi> and <hi>ineffectual.</hi> If all the Tenants of a Mannor should swear not to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend the Court, the Oath would not only be <hi>illegal</hi> in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect of the Tenants, but <hi>vain</hi> in reference to the Lord.
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:205037:11"/>The Oath is not design'd to take away <hi>Jurisdiction</hi> from the Judge; but to take away some <hi>Liberty</hi> from the Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low; If Men should upon Oath submit to Referees or Arbitrators, the Power of the Courts would not be dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish'd, but the Right of the Subjects restrain'd; for it is a vain and senseless conceit, that if my Authority, of what Nature soever, whether from King or Subject be legally vest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in me, any Man by <hi>his</hi> Oath <hi>can swear away my Jurisdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. This Opinion as absurd as it now seems, is more so, if as really, there is not, are there be no such Oath at all: A Fellow renounces indeed Appeals in General, and those Words of Latitude are put into a certain and determinate Signification.</p>
            <p>Now the <hi>Visitor</hi> cannot come under those Words, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever large and extensive; the <hi>Visitor</hi> hath a domestick and internal <hi>Forum;</hi> and whereas a Complaint to him is an application to an <hi>ordinary</hi> Judge; An Appeal in propriet of Speech is a recourse to a <hi>forreign</hi> or <hi>superior</hi> and <hi>extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary</hi> Jurisdiction: In all Abbies, and in all Colleges, in all Instances of Canon and Common Law, these general Words excluded any other Authority, except that of the <hi>Visitor;</hi> but did secure and strengthen his Jurisdiction. And therefore when the Statutes of <hi>Exeter</hi> College were made, the Founders well knew the Power of the <hi>Visitor</hi> as set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by Law; they knew the Practice of all Colleges, from whence these Statutes were transcrib'd; and therefore if they had design'd to put any <hi>new</hi> Limitations to the <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sitors</hi> Authority; it is impossible to think but they would have found out <hi>new</hi> Words to express their Intention.
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:205037:11"/>These Statutes, however ancient the College is, are of a late date; the Usage of all other Colleges was then known and fixt, and therefore if any more than the customary Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nunciation had been design'd, the usual Oath would never have been borrow'd and impos'd. All Letters of great Men are renounc'd; all forreign and vexatious Suits are for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden, and would it not have been as easie (since he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scended to particulars) to bestow one word upon the <hi>Visi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor,</hi> and at least <hi>by Name</hi> to <hi>exclude him?</hi> The Absurdity of that Opinion, if it needs be further demonstrated, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears most visibly in this following Instance: The <hi>Rector</hi> is by Oath barr'd as much from all these <hi>juris &amp; facti re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediis per quae possit in integrum restitui,</hi> and renounces them <hi>in vim pacti,</hi> as well as the Fellows; and yet in the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute he is expresly allow'd to appeal to the <hi>Visitor.</hi> Now would a <hi>Founder</hi> give a Man a Liberty by Statute, which he takes away by <hi>Oath?</hi> Would he settle a Right in the <hi>Rector</hi> in one Statute, and oblige him to swear himself out of it in another? It is clear then, that the <hi>Visitor</hi> was not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the purview of that <hi>Oath,</hi> and that the <hi>Rector</hi> would have been guilty of no <hi>Perjury</hi> for appealing <hi>to him.</hi> But I leave it to his <hi>Polonian Casuists</hi> to distinguish him out of it upon his farther <hi>Appeal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If then the <hi>Visitor</hi> hath <hi>general</hi> Powers vested in him by Law and by Statute; if he is the <hi>Conservator</hi> of the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege; and as in their <hi>Acts</hi> he is formerly call'd <hi>Patronus,</hi> and <hi>Supremus Judex</hi> therein; if he can redress all Griev<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances, and hath consequently the Power of Receiving Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peals; it is not possible that a <hi>Fellow</hi>'s Oath, tho it should have particularly nam'd him, can devest him of that Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority;
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:205037:12"/>and if such Oath doth <hi>not</hi> particularly name him, nor by Comparison with other Statutes, was intended to exclude his Jurisdiction, it is certain that the Authority remains <hi>entire;</hi> and, that in the same manner as Appeals lay to him before the Oath, they must be admitted to lie after it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The second Exception to this Universal Authority is drawn from the Words of the Statute <hi>de Vis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Eâ de Causâ liceat Domino Episcopo</hi> Exon, <hi>qui pro tempore fuerit, &amp; nulli alii, nec aliis, quoties per Rectorem dicti Coll. &amp; in ejus absentia Subrectorem, &amp; quatuor alios ad minus, ex septem maximè Senioribus Scholaribus fuerit requisitus; Nec non absque requisitione ulla de quinquennio in quinquennium semel ad dictum Coll. per se, vel per suum Commissarium, quem duxe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, deputandum liberè accedere.</hi> Cui <hi>quidem Reverend. Patri, ac Deputato suo</hi> (praeterea nemini) <hi>tanquam Patrono &amp; Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rio Visitatori, vigore praesentis statuti plenam concedimus potesta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem, ut super omnibus &amp; singulis particulis &amp; articulis, in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctis Statutis contentis, ac de quibuscunque aliis Articulis statum, commodum, aut honorem dicti Coll. concernentibus aut quae in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cto Coll. aut aliqua illius Persona fuerint reformanda, aut cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rigenda, Rectorem, Scholares, &amp; Electos interroget, &amp; inquirat, cogátque eorum unumquenque in Virtute Juramenti, &amp;</hi> per cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suras <hi>si opus fuerit ad dicendum veritatem de praemissis omnibus singulis, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It hath been before prov'd, that <hi>two</hi> Powers are necessa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily lodg'd in a Visitour; one is the <hi>ordinary jurisdiction,</hi> which exerts it self upon the injury and complaint of any of his Subjects; and redresses their grievances: The other is an extraordinary and <hi>general enquiry</hi> made by <hi>the Judge</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:205037:12"/>himself <hi>ex officio</hi> without the instance of the Party. Now this Statute doth not only vest him by the former general words with the <hi>ordinary</hi> powers necessarily incident to a Visitor's Office: But goes on likewise to <hi>ascertain</hi> here his <hi>extraordinary</hi> Authority and to fix the <hi>bounds</hi> of it. This <hi>Visitation</hi> is general as well in respect of <hi>Crimes</hi> as <hi>Persons</hi> within the Judges territory and compass; and is sometimes <hi>necessary</hi> and therefore <hi>not omitted;</hi> but withal troublesome and <hi>chargeable,</hi> and therefore <hi>restrain'd.</hi> In this general en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry <hi>by Office</hi> which is by the Canonists call'd <hi>Officium merum</hi> the powers of the Judge are much larger than upon an <hi>Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal;</hi> the method of the procedure different, and the occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of it are of as great, yet usually not of so urgent and pressing necessity. And therefore since his Powers are <hi>great;</hi> the solemnity of the Process extraordinary; and the <hi>Sportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lage</hi> which is always incident to it, not small; it was pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in the Founder to allow the use of <hi>ordinary</hi> Jurisdiction <hi>always;</hi> and by that means to prevent the necessity, as well as to restrain the exercise of his <hi>extraordinary Authority.</hi> And herein the care of the Founder was agreeable to that of the Church, for no <hi>Canons</hi> ever set bounds to any other than gainful Visitations, nor ever thought fit to limit the Duty, but where it was recommended by Proxies.</p>
            <p>As this Jurisdiction then is set up by Statute; so another, in Case of great emergencies is likewise plac'd in the Visitor; which is a <hi>Visitation upon requisition.</hi> This is a mixt Office; and differs from a Visitation because it is granted upon <hi>denun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciation</hi> and <hi>presentment,</hi> and upon the instance of the party; and yet at the same time agrees not with Appeal; because it proceeds by Enquiry and tends not to the <hi>redress</hi> of a
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:205037:13"/>private grievance, but the <hi>regulation</hi> of some publick enor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity.</p>
            <p>This Branch of the Statute therefore, however it may limit a <hi>Visitation,</hi> is so far from restraining <hi>Appeals,</hi> that it enforces them; for where-ever the extraordinary <hi>Remedies</hi> are limited, there is more occasion for, and more Latitude to be given to, the <hi>Ordinary Jurisdiction.</hi> This is the plain and natural intendment of the <hi>Statute;</hi> this is that <hi>Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sal Provision</hi> which the <hi>Founder</hi> design'd, which the <hi>College</hi> need, and which the <hi>Visitatorial Power</hi> was brought in to sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply. Upon this short view of the Office of <hi>Visitor</hi> in general, and upon this enquiry into the Statutes of <hi>Exeter College,</hi> in particular, it may be safely affirm'd.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>That all sole</hi> Visitors <hi>separately, and all</hi> Visitors <hi>ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary, and extraordinary joyntly, have as an incident to their Office, the Power of receiving</hi> Appeals.</item>
               <item>2. <hi>That this Power, as in all</hi> Churches, Monasteries <hi>and</hi> Hospitals, <hi>so in all</hi> Colleges <hi>hath by the respective</hi> Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sitors <hi>thereof, been us'd and exercis'd, and in all Courts been confirm'd and allow'd.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3. <hi>That the Local Statutes of</hi> Exeter College <hi>do in the same, and no other manner, then as the Canons and as the Statutes of most other Colleges, limit and restrain the so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn, extraordinary, and chargeable</hi> Visitations; <hi>but at the same time do vest the</hi> Visitor <hi>of the College, with all ordinary Jurisdiction in its full extent and latitude.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>4. <hi>That the Statutes of</hi> Exeter College <hi>are so far from precluding Appeals to the</hi> Visitor, <hi>that they expresly war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant them, and that the</hi> Oaths <hi>of the</hi> Rector <hi>and</hi> Fellows
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:205037:13"/>
                  <hi>neither can, nor by the plain and natural sense of the Words, are intended to restrain this Authority.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>If then the <hi>Visitor</hi> hath power of receiving Appeals, Dr. <hi>Masters</hi> Commission is good, Dr. <hi>Bury rightly</hi> as well as <hi>justly</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell'd, and the whole <hi>Process</hi> legal and unquestionable.
<note n="*" place="bottom">
                  <hi>See the Account of the Proceedings,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>P.</hi> 26, 27.</note> It is not necessary therefore to add what yet hath been ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parently prov'd, and will more fully be clear'd, that if the Bishop had <hi>no</hi> Power of receiving Appeals, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sequently the Commission was void, and the Acts of it <hi>null</hi> and <hi>inauthoritative,</hi> yet however the <hi>Visitation</hi> could not thereby be barr'd, nor the Bishops Right be taken away, nor the Expulsion defeated.</p>
            <p>The Point being thus setled, it will be an easier Matter to consider those little Objections, which have been start<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Author of the <hi>Case,</hi> and have not yet been refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by Mr. <hi>Colmer.</hi> Some things there are in the <hi>Account,</hi> which he says he does not <hi>understand,</hi> and perhaps it may be no easie Matter for me to bring <hi>down</hi> my Expressions to his <hi>Understanding;</hi> or his <hi>Understanding</hi> up to them: Other Passages there are that in his Opinion need no Answer, and they therefore stand in the same <hi>Condition</hi> they were, and want no Defence: But as to the Exceptions taken, they shall have Answers that are very short; and yet as I sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose, full, and no otherwise tedious, then because super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluous and unnecessary.</p>
            <p>After the History of Mr. <hi>Colmers</hi> Incontinence, which has been prov'd to be False and Immaterial; the first <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>position</hi> laid down is, That an Appeal to the Visitour is <hi>by
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:205037:14"/>Oaths</hi> restrain'd; and then he gives you a Comment on the reasons of that Restraint.</p>
            <p>For when he hath put strange Orders on the Founder, which he never made: then he gives the Grounds, which induc'd the Founder to the making of those Orders.</p>
            <p>The Ground then, that is reasonably supposed to perswade him to this <hi>Policy,</hi> was the Peace and Quiet of the House: And,</p>
            <p>Were not all other <hi>Societies</hi> of <hi>Students</hi> as much design'd for Peace and Quietness as <hi>Exeter</hi> College? Had not Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nasteries Free-Chappels, and Religious Societies as little occasion for Disturbances and Quarrels as Colleges? And were not their Founders weak Men to bring them into Noise, Feuds and Dissensions, when they appointed a Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sitour, and gave him due Power of redressing their Grievan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and of deciding their Controversies? Would there not be much more Peace in a Diocess, if the Clergy were not subject to Visitation? And if a Parson, whose Study and Profession entitle him to Quiet, might not be cited from his Home, and subjected to the Complaint of every vex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atious Person only for <hi>Heresie, Bribery,</hi> and <hi>Incontinency?</hi> What Confusion and Disturbances the Statute of <hi>Hen.</hi> 5. occasioned in <hi>England,</hi> when it subjected Hospitals to Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sitation, whose Members before, were <hi>without any noise</hi> robb'd and despoil'd, and whose Revenues had been very <hi>quietly lost,</hi> and dilapidated? In short, the taking away of <hi>Westminster</hi>-Hall would be an effective Remedy against Champerty and Maintenance, and troublesom Law-Suits and Contention would quickly cease, if we would remove the Courts, in which they are to be ended.</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:205037:14"/>
            <p>But now for once I would desire him to make as many <hi>reasonable Supposals,</hi> as he will for the late Rector, and such Fellows of <hi>Exeter</hi> College as imploy'd him; but as few as possible for the Founders, who neither need nor desire his assistance. The Founders were Wise-Men, <hi>Stapul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> was a learned Bishop: Sir <hi>William Petre</hi> a prudent States<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, and therefore such <hi>reasonable Supposals,</hi> tho of a Piece with the rest of the Book, are ill suited to the Character of the <hi>Persons introduc'd.</hi> All the Peace and Quiet which the College can aim at, or hope for, is promoted by the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of a <hi>Visitor,</hi> and their particular Happiness consists in having their Controversies decided in a <hi>private</hi> and <hi>dome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stick</hi> Court. And tho the Censures of a <hi>Visitor</hi> may be troublesom to those Persons that deserve them; and a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>view of the Cause try'd is not very acceptable to some Judges; yet certain it is, that nothing is more requisite than the Visitatorial <hi>Power,</hi> for the due government of the <hi>Society,</hi> for the prevention of Grievances, and Exorbitances; for the speedy determination of Controversies; and for the settlement of Peace and Quietness in the College. Especi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally since, if there be no <hi>Visitor</hi> that can give redress to a Fellow unjustly expell'd; It is plain that a <hi>Mandamus</hi> would lie for him, as well as <hi>for a Parish Clark;</hi> and that this admirable Method <hi>of producing Peace</hi> and <hi>Quiet,</hi> would draw the Cause from the <hi>Visitor</hi> into <hi>Westminster-Hall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The next thing that he leaves me to explain, is an Oath, being accessory to a Statute: Where-ever an Oath is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lative to the Law, and the Sense of one depends on the meaning of the other, and the Obligation of one, relies on the continuance of the other, here it is accessory to it.
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:205037:15"/>Now then, <hi>Si continget me per Rectorem aut in hujusmodi interesse habentes corrigi, puniri, aut à dicti Coll. sustentatione ejici &amp; expelli, excludi, privari vel amoveri propter mea forsan demerita, ipsum Rectorem, seu alias Personas, seu eorum ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quem, &amp;c. quantumcun{que} alias mihi probitatis &amp; vitae me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rita suffragentur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In this Case therefore the <hi>demerita</hi> are (as is elsewhere ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain'd) <hi>Causae in Statutis contentae:</hi> The <hi>interesse habentes</hi> are such as are appointed by Statute; and since it is impossible to know the extent of the Oath without recourse to the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute: The Oath is accessory to it, and guided by it.</p>
            <p>And if the Statutes are alter'd by legal Authority: The matter of the Oath is likewise chang'd, not the obligation; and the Oath, as strongly obliges to the performance of the new Law, as once of the old.</p>
            <p n="2">2. He proves that <hi>legitimè convictus</hi> doth not mean a convi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction according <hi>to the Law of England.</hi> For it is plain to him that the <hi>Rectour</hi> of the College cannot impannel a Jury; nor administer an Oath. This is the <hi>Phantom</hi> that he raises; and, being his own, it is easily refuted even by himself: For no Man else was so absurd as to imagine, That when the Founder had in every thing else pursued the Terms and Rules of <hi>Canon</hi> Law, he would have borrowed the proof only of a charge from the <hi>Common:</hi> But if <hi>legitima convictio</hi> doth not amount to a conviction by a Jury; must it mean nothing, or must it signifie a conviction <hi>without,</hi> or <hi>against</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aw? for if it doth not, it will not justifie Mr. <hi>Colmer</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulsion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Legitima convictio</hi> is such a conviction as the Statutes direct; and where the Statutes are silent, is such a conviction, as the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:205037:15"/>Law require, in conformity to which these Statutes are made. The method of the Conviction in divers Laws is very often different; but it is always grounded on a <hi>crime,</hi> and no crime can be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied to a person but by proof. In common Law a Verdict is founded upon evidence; and is presumed to be made in pursuance of it; In Canon law, where Trials are made by Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesses, not by Jury, nothing but the confession of the Parties, the Testimony of two witnesses, or the <hi>Notoriety of the Fact</hi> can make a <hi>Conviction.</hi> And therefore as in one the Sentence of a Judge cannot convict any man, when <hi>supported by no ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict;</hi> so in the other it is equally void, when founded on <hi>no evidence.</hi> A man cannot renounce his Right to legal Proceedings; If he should agree to be fentenced uncited and unheard, and to be convicted without proofs; it is a void Agreement, and so utterly null and illegal; that the <hi>vis pacti</hi> cannot support it: <hi>Sententia nulla potest partium consensu ut valeat, non tanquam sententia sed tanquam contractus: Cald. Cons.</hi> 138.</p>
            <p>The Fellows of <hi>Exeter</hi> might be convicted of Incontinence, as the Statutes of other Colleges direct <hi>per idoneos testes, &amp; facti evidentiam;</hi> or as Clarks are to be convict of it, <hi>according to such lawful proofs</hi> as are <hi>requisite by the law of the Church:</hi> 1 H. 7. c. 4. The Rector, if he cannot administer an Oath, might have used the assistance of the <hi>Vice-Chancellors</hi> or of the Visitors Juridiction. <hi>Homicide</hi> is in the Ecclesiastical Court a cause of <hi>Deprivation;</hi> and yet it cannot originally be examined there: Their Sentence must be built on a Conviction at Common law: and as the Spiritual Judges even to Ecclesiastical purposes cannot convict Men of such crime by Ecclesiastical Proofs; so much less can they declare men convict without any. <hi>Hob.</hi> 122. <hi>Searls Case. Cr.</hi> 2. <hi>Hob.</hi> 194. <hi>A competent Judge</hi> then is not more required, than <hi>Legal Testimonie; Summarie de plano &amp; extrà strepitum Judicialem</hi> may take away the formality of the Process, but never the necessity of Evidence; The noise of an Oath is not great; nor the length of it tedious; It is the direct and plain way of Procedure; and all Presumptions, strained Infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences, and traditional Reports occasion the length and circuit of a Tryal.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Legitimè</hi> is expounded in the Probationers Oath <hi>secundum exigentiam Statutorum,</hi> and so <hi>Canonice</hi> is interpreted <hi>secun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:205037:16"/>exigentium Canonum.</hi> Lindw. 5. Tit. de Purg. Canon.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Si propter mea demerita contingat me deprivari</hi> is in some statutes of other Colleges explained <hi>propter mea demerita, aut causas in statutis contentas;</hi> in others propter <hi>malos mores, aut mea demerita.</hi> Now this Gentleman's interpretation of <hi>ob mea demerita</hi> is <hi>whether</hi> a <hi>man be guilty or no,</hi> which then should have been thus expressed <hi>ob mea forsan non demerita.</hi> And if <hi>non</hi> added to this and most of his affirmations, it would much ease the Book of many falshoods, and make it in many other instances, true sence, as in this good Grammar: But the following words put the sence of it out of doubt, <hi>quamvis alias mihi probitatis &amp; vitae merita suffragentur:</hi> Which imply a Man criminal in <hi>this,</hi> and irrepoveable in <hi>all other</hi> concerns. The Oath was designed to oblige the Conscience; if the Crime was true, Acquiescence was enjoyned; if it was false, no just remedy was precluded. And whether the charge were true or false, his Conscience is judge; and his Oath enforces the Conscience to a right judgment.</p>
            <p>If then an innocent man had liberty of Appeal; whoever doth not appeal confesses, and owns his guilt. <hi>Non appellans dicitur ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probare sententiam latam Card. Tusc. con.</hi> 388.</p>
            <p n="5">5. My 4th. reason was this. <q>That it is the plain design of this Oath to secure the College from any <hi>Action at Law,</hi> or any other disturbance <hi>from abroad;</hi> and that in the recital of the different appeals, and remedies, which are there prohibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that of <hi>appeal to the Visitor,</hi> which was most obvious to to be thought on, is not <hi>expresly</hi> mentioned nor forbidden: And therefore that those general words may in an equitable sence be intended to restrain the Party from all Appeals to an <hi>Extraneous,</hi> not to a <hi>Domestic</hi> Court; to one that is a <hi>Foreign</hi> Judge, not to a <hi>Visitor,</hi> who is a <hi>part</hi> and the <hi>first member</hi> of <hi>the</hi> College.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Nothing in the answer deserves to be confidered; but the dome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stick Jurisdiction of a <hi>Visitor;</hi> if the <hi>Founder</hi> referred all <hi>jurgia irae &amp; rixae</hi> to the final arbitration of the <hi>Rector, Subrector</hi> and three <hi>Seniors;</hi> The Jurisdiction of those persons thereby gained in respect of the <hi>Visitor</hi> was <hi>cumulative,</hi> not <hi>privative.</hi> And therefore when
<note place="bottom">
                  <hi>See. Case</hi> p. 26.</note>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:205037:16"/>a man is forbidden, as in this case, to prosecute another <hi>corant aliquo Judice extrinseco Ecclesiastico vel Saeculari;</hi> the intent of the <hi>Founder</hi> plainly appears to bar any action in the <hi>spiritual</hi> and <hi>temporal</hi> Court; and to refer the contending Parties to the Arbitrators there mentioned or at farthest to no other than some <hi>intrinsick Judge.</hi> And it is observable that these little Controversies were not to be <hi>Judicially</hi> ended by these Persons; but <hi>aliquâ ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione bonâ &amp; concordiâ per personas praedictas (as Referees</hi> and <hi>Arbitra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors,) terminentur &amp; finiantur:</hi> so that here an amicable reference is advised and <hi>enjoyned;</hi> but still upon a farther disagreement, if it could not take effect every Action <hi>coram aliquo Judice extrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seco</hi> was <hi>expressly</hi> forbidden; but not a recourse to a <hi>Visitor</hi> disal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed.</p>
            <p>The Argument concerning <hi>John a Stiles,</hi> and the 6th. <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment</hi> needs no grave answer; and I have at present nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther will nor leisure to expose it.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Arbitrary power is power against law: And the unstatutable Expulsion of a Fellow; and the denial of a lawfull Appeal are illegal and arbitrary Acts: what obligations the <hi>Founder</hi> might have enjoyned we dispute not; but we have proved, that none are laid: The <hi>Visitors</hi> Authority is not created by the local Statutes, but cast upon him by law; The Power of a <hi>Visitour</hi> depends not on the <hi>Founder,</hi> but the Right of the Bishop of <hi>Exeter</hi> to that power is derived from <hi>him:</hi> The Kings Courts have a more <hi>large</hi> Jurisdisdiction than the <hi>Visitor;</hi> but not more <hi>certain.</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore no mans Oath can bar the Power of the one, nor of the other; especially since it appears, that it was not designed to preclude them.</p>
            <p>Thus hath it once more been proved; That the Oath is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary to the Statute, that no innocent Man is barr'd from <hi>Appeal;</hi> that legal Proofs are necessary to a legal Conviction, that the <hi>Visitor</hi> is a <hi>Domestick</hi> Judge, and that <hi>appeals</hi> to him from an innocent person, illegally expelled, are not more warranted by Reason, than by Statute.</p>
            <p>Next, the <hi>Case</hi> examines the reasons that proved the <hi>Visitors</hi> Authority of <hi>receiving Appeals.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>P. 36. It is owned, That there are no other Judges of <hi>Appeal</hi> except the <hi>Visitor;</hi> but it is doubted whether there are any Judges of them at all. An <hi>Appeal</hi> is a natural Defence which cannot
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:205037:17"/>be taken away by any Prince or Power; much less by any other than by the supreme Magistrate and not justly by him. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is not easy to conceive, especially if we read his words, that a <hi>private Founder</hi> ever designed to preclude it. For since <hi>Appellatione remotâ</hi> is never mentioned in the Statutes but once, and since then it expressly bars an <hi>Appeal from</hi> the <hi>Visitor</hi> not <hi>to</hi> him; no part of the Statutes can be urged against the <hi>Visitors</hi> authority, but the Oath of the Fellows. That Oath hath been already proved to bar no <hi>Appeal</hi> to the <hi>Visitor;</hi> and the rather is not capable of that sence; because all Statutes that take away <hi>Appeals</hi> are <hi>odiosa,</hi> and therefore in doubtful cases are limited and restrained; and all renunciations of right must and ought to be construed in <hi>favorem renunciantis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If then a <hi>Visitor</hi> had power of <hi>receiving Appeals,</hi> if in this College <hi>all</hi> other <hi>Judges</hi> but the Bishop of <hi>Exeter</hi> are expresly excluded; if the Oath doth not take away the Fellow's right, much less the Bishops Jurisdiction; then it follows, that the Bishop had a Right of receiving Appeals; incident to the Office of a Visitor, and yet distinct from his Right of <hi>a General Visitation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <q>To dream of universality of Jurisdiction from a sound of a word <hi>Ordinarius</hi> is a conceit that needs no more refutation, than the mentioning of it.</q> And to dream of the visitation in five years from the sound of the word <hi>Quinquennium</hi> is equally as senseless, and ridiculous. The import and meaning of both words is fixt and known, and the one is not, as I think more <hi>sounding</hi> than the other. The only difference is, that the latter by chance fell within his reach, and the former is undoubtedly above it. Usually legal Controversies depend on the doubtful meaning of Terms; The case is altered by the extent, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>striction of a word: and therefore it was <hi>once</hi> a frequent obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation in the Law books; That the true knowledge of terms is the most necessary and most difficult part of that Study. What <hi>ordinarius</hi> signifies; I have before explained, and any judicious man, that reads those great and express authorities will, choose rather to <hi>dream</hi> with those Authors than to <hi>think</hi> with this Gentleman.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The little Objections that follow are already anticipated and
<note place="bottom">
                  <hi>Coke</hi> 4. <hi>Inst.</hi> p. 340, <hi>Patrick</hi>'s <hi>Case Card. Tusc.</hi> c. 345. <hi>Bald. Cons.</hi> 144. <hi>Al.</hi> 113. n. 7.</note>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:205037:17"/>prevented; only one thing I must observe, that the <hi>operative</hi> and <hi>effective</hi> words of the Statute are here stiled the Preamble of it: the Statute it self, as before printed and explained, sufficiently shows the weakness of the Assertion; and all the long Harangue founded on that bottom, is a gross continued mistake, made acceptable however to some Palates, by much scurrility, and no wit.</p>
            <p>Men that have no Reputation themselves, may fall upon their Betters without danger; and the return of the Compliment is as prejudicial to the Person affronted, as the abuse it self, because it implies an equality. Libels that have shewn the Malice, have some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times recommended the Wit of the Adversary; but blunt downright Rudeness is always the joynt product of ill nature and stupidity: however it is not improper that the late <hi>Rectors</hi> Cause should be defended with the <hi>same</hi> decency, with which it was managed, and that the Advocate should at once shew himself Master as well of the Sence as of the good Breeding of his Client.</p>
            <p>The Appointment of the <hi>Founder</hi> created him <hi>Visitor,</hi> but the Law ascertain'd and fix'd the Rights of his Office. A <hi>College</hi> and an <hi>Hospital</hi> is as much <hi>visitable</hi> in Law as a <hi>Church.</hi> And the same right that of necessity belongs to the <hi>Visitor</hi> of a <hi>Diocess,</hi> must of Law belong to the Visitor of a <hi>College:</hi> The Precincts may be more narrow, but the Jurisdiction is as large; the Subjects may be fewer, but the Powers are as many. The <hi>Ordinary</hi> Acts of Visitation therefore remain equally in both, since (as hath been already prov'd,) the Bounds that are set, reach only to the <hi>extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary</hi> Acts of their Power, and their solemn Visitations.</p>
            <p>It being evident then that both these Powers, both of <hi>receiving Appeals,</hi> and of a <hi>General Visitation,</hi> tho they are both equally lodg'd in the <hi>Visitor,</hi> yet are both <hi>entire</hi> and <hi>distinct</hi> from each other in their nature; it will be easie to prove that the <hi>exercise</hi> of one cannot bar the Bishop from the <hi>right</hi> to the other: This task is still the less difficult, because the reasons in the Account for it are such, as the <hi>Case</hi> hath not yet pretended to answer.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Bishop of <hi>Exeter</hi> then hath no power but as <hi>Visitor,</hi> but o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Powers belong to the <hi>Visitor</hi> thanthat of a <hi>Visitation:</hi> A distinct Authority of a <hi>general enquiry</hi> is given to him, and if a <hi>Commission</hi> of <hi>Appeal</hi> amounts not to this Power, it cannot determine it. An <hi>Appeal</hi> is private in its end, and restrain'd in its extent: A <hi>Visitation</hi>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:205037:18"/>is of a publick nature, and general in its designs as well as powers: Both indeed may in their own nature be Criminal, but the one is prosecuted <hi>Civiliter,</hi> the other <hi>Criminaliter;</hi> the one tends to the <hi>redress</hi> of a <hi>Grievance,</hi> the other to the <hi>punishment</hi> of a <hi>Crime.</hi> 'Tis said indeed in the <hi>Case,</hi> that <hi>omne majus continet in se minus;</hi> and that if it makes out any thing, must prove, that whoever hath <hi>right</hi> of <hi>Visitation,</hi> hath <hi>power</hi> of <hi>receiving Appeals.</hi> But such a Maxim as <hi>Omne minus continet in se majus,</hi> can only convince us, that a <hi>Commission</hi> of <hi>Appeal</hi> contains a <hi>Visitation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The Commission by which Dr. <hi>Master</hi> acted, was founded on that part of the Statute, by which the Bishop is appointed and constituted <hi>Visitor</hi> in <hi>General;</hi> not that which gives him power of a <hi>Quinquennial Visitation.</hi> He has no other claim to this Authority, then as <hi>Visitor;</hi> and and therefore in his Commission, he sets forth his own Title, and withal the ground of his Power. If any <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dundant</hi> words were there, they could do no harm, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore are <hi>weakly</hi> excepted against. But as it happens, those only are used, that are sufficient to support the delegated Jurisdiction.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The <hi>Nature</hi> of a Commission appears not from the <hi>Stile</hi> or <hi>Title</hi> of the Judge, but from the <hi>extent</hi> or <hi>restraint</hi> of the <hi>Powers</hi> that are granted. The <hi>being</hi> of a Court can be no other than such as is warranted by a Commission on which it depends: This was wholly restrained to the Cause of <hi>Appeal,</hi> and the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>missary</hi> exactly observ'd the restrictions. In a <hi>Visitation, all</hi> the Fellows must necessarily have been cited, and appeared; but <hi>none</hi> were call'd to this <hi>Court,</hi> but those that had been partakers of the Personal wrong, and were oblig'd to answer the charge of Mr. <hi>Colmar</hi> against them.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The <hi>Definition</hi> of a <hi>Visitation</hi> then is <hi>weakly</hi> applied to the <hi>Commission</hi> of <hi>Appeal;</hi> the <hi>nature</hi> of <hi>Vistation</hi> hath been prov'd to be a voluntary enquiry into matters <hi>Criminal,</hi> and <hi>Correction</hi> thereupon, and to be <hi>general</hi> likewise, both as to <hi>Crimes</hi> and <hi>Persons.</hi> Now how was this a <hi>voluntary</hi> enquiry, that was made not by the Judge himself <hi>ex Officio,</hi> but at the <hi>instance</hi> of Mr. <hi>Colmar?</hi> How was it <hi>general,</hi> that took Conusance only of <hi>this</hi> Crime, and of <hi>no</hi> other Persons than of such as were concern'd in it?</p>
            <p>Nor lastly, can it be properly said to be an Enquiry into mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters <hi>Criminal,</hi> which only examined a Crime upon the instance
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:205037:18"/>of a Party, in order to his <hi>private</hi> amends and satisfaction. Since therefore the Commission was <hi>Special,</hi> and restrain'd <hi>ad negotium appellationis</hi> only, since the <hi>Acta Curiae,</hi> which are here annex'd, were in pursuance of that Authority, and exceeded not those re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strictions: Since the right of <hi>receiving Appeals</hi> is wholly different from that of a <hi>Visitation,</hi> the Powers much <hi>less,</hi> the Extent and Process more <hi>confin'd;</hi> it is impossible that this Act can amount to a <hi>Visitation,</hi> or that the <hi>exercise</hi> of <hi>one</hi> Authority, can deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine the Bishops <hi>right</hi> to the <hi>other.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ground I believe of this <hi>Authors</hi> mistake was this, that where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver a Person hath any right of doing any Act, Act of the same na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture shall without the special Declaration of the Party, by intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Law, in his favour, be presum'd to be Authoritative and Legal. This Rule, as it holds not in this Case, because <hi>both</hi> Powers were lodg'd in the <hi>Visitor,</hi> so neither, upon the <hi>supposed</hi> failure of <hi>one</hi> of those Jurisdictions, could it reach it: For those Acts must be of the <hi>same</hi> nature, and from the near <hi>affinity</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them and the <hi>equality</hi> of the extent, one is said to amount to the other. Besides that Rule takes in only those Acts which are <hi>undetermin'd</hi> by the Party, and therefore liable to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction of Law: Whereever Words are <hi>plain</hi> and <hi>express,</hi> there is no room for <hi>implication,</hi> and an intendment may be presumed <hi>without</hi> the Declaration of the Parties, but not <hi>against</hi> it. 1 Just. 245. <hi>c.</hi> 1. Instit. 49. b. Perk. fol. 55 and 56.40. Ed. 3.5. <hi>Inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio me a nomen imponit operi meo.</hi> Hob. <hi>Pitts v. James</hi> p. 123. Now in this Case therefore, not only the <hi>Commission</hi> shew'd the special intent of the Party; but the <hi>Commissary</hi> himself openly declar'd, That he did not then come upon a <hi>Visitation,</hi> and therefore <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fas'd</hi> the <hi>Sportulage</hi> in that case appointed by the <hi>Founder.</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendments therefore and Implications are at an end, and the <hi>Commission</hi> it self, if it should be void, would have been a <hi>null</hi> and <hi>inauthoritative</hi> act, and not a <hi>Visitation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The main point being thus settled, I shall further examine what is <hi>material</hi> in the <hi>Case,</hi> thinking it more worth while to <hi>refute</hi> the <hi>Arguments,</hi> than, as I easily might, to <hi>expose</hi> the <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor.</hi> All that is afterwards Considerable, falls under these Heads.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That by Censures in the Statute, <hi>Ecclesiastical</hi> Censures are not meant.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:205037:19"/>2. That the Right Reverend the Visitor, for inflicting of <hi>Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clesiastical</hi> Censures, is guilty of a <hi>Praemunire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. That Dr. <hi>Hern</hi>'s Place was not void by Statute.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That the <hi>Visitor</hi> had no Power by Statute of <hi>Suspending</hi> the Fellows <hi>ab Officio.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. That the <hi>Visitor</hi> ought not to have been Judge in his own Cause, nor to have pronounc'd for his own Jurisdiction.</p>
            <p n="6">6. That the Concurrence of the Fellows to the Rectors Expul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion was not Statutable. And</p>
            <p>Lastly, That <hi>Contumacy</hi> is no <hi>Statutable</hi> cause of Expulsion; and if it were, ought in the case of the <hi>Fellows</hi> as well as the <hi>Rector</hi> to receive the same Punishment from the <hi>Visitor.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. As to the Censures.</p>
            <p>The Statute says, <hi>Visitator cogat eorum unumquen{que} in virtute juramenti &amp; per Censuras si opus fuerit ad dicendam veritatem de praemissis.</hi> As for <hi>Censura</hi> then this Author turn'd his Dictiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and found that sometimes it signified a <hi>reprehension.</hi> As tho any term used in Law had not a primitive sense and meaning, and was not afterwards as all words of Art in their respective profession limited and restrained only to the <hi>borrowed Signification.</hi> Any Manthat knows the constant custom of enforcing Men to testify the truth <hi>per juramentum &amp; censuras</hi> the usual <hi>Compulsories</hi> in all Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clesiastical Courts, will smile at any other interpretation. See <hi>Reg. br. orig, fol.</hi> 36.6. <hi>tit. Proh. Card. Tus. Con.</hi> 189. <hi>Scard. fol.</hi> 450. That I may not trouble the Reader with Instances, I will only observe, that in Acts of Parliament frequently, and in rules of Canon Law always, and in Statutes of Colledges, which were made in pursuance of the Canons, constantly, <hi>Censures</hi> do and must mean no more than the Three famous and well known Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siastical Censures. And I refer this Rule more particularly to this Gentleman's Interpretation, <hi>Judex Accademiarum solet ferre censur as etiam in Laicos studiosos, &amp; in causis temporalibus, unde studiorum gratiâ non est prohibitum Judici Academiae, ut sua etiam Jurisdictione Ecclesiasticâ utatur; quò efficacius saecularem exerceat? Mendo de ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re Acad.</hi> p. 252. What do Censures mean there, a Rebuke, or a Reprehension, or a Sentence in the Star chamber? or have they a relation to the old Roman Censures? If this be design'd for Wit, it is not very agreeable; but if it be Ignorance, as I suppose, it is extreamly gross.</p>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:205037:19"/>
            <p>Bonacina <hi>Tom.</hi> 1. <hi>Disp,</hi> 2. <hi>de Excom.</hi> talks of <hi>Censura quibus superi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ores</hi> (speaking of Visitours) <hi>praecipiunt sibi aliquid revelari. D'avila de Cens. Eccl. C.</hi> 3. <hi>D.</hi> 1. <hi>Visitatores bene possunt relinquere Ordinatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes in scriptis cum poenâ Excommunicationis;</hi> and so <hi>Visitatores Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gionum</hi> (of all religious Houses) <hi>possunt relinquere Ordinationes in Scriptis cum poena Excommunicationis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How far therefore the <hi>Founder</hi> could vest the <hi>Visitor</hi> with this Authority, and how far the Law will warrant it, is matter of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother dispute: But that <hi>Visitors</hi> have in like Cases used <hi>Ecclesi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>astical Censures,</hi> even in Societies not merely <hi>Ecclesiastical</hi> and that the <hi>Founder</hi> design'd by these Words to give that Power, and esteem'd it necessary for the <hi>Visitor,</hi> is and will be prov'd beyond Contradiction.</p>
            <p n="2">2. As to the <hi>Praemunire.</hi> If this Authour had given the Reason upon which the learned Judges granted a <hi>Prohibition</hi> in his Case, the force of their Argument and the Authority of the Persons would justly have commanded an entire Submission and Acquies<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence; at least nothing further would have been mov'd than that upon the Prayer of a <hi>Consultation,</hi> their Lordships would be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, according to their Wisdom, finally to settle and determine the Cause. But now, since he hath been pleased to impose his own Opinions upon the World, and with equal Insolence and Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance to pass Sentence upon the Bishop himself, and to <hi>pronounce</hi> him guilty of a <hi>Praemunire:</hi> it is not to be expected, that the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference should be paid to his weak <hi>Argument,</hi> which undoubted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly would have been due to his <hi>Report.</hi> The Discourse that he there gives is well proportion'd to the Capacity and the Breeding of his Client; and if the Cause be good in it self, it is there put in so ill a Light, and justify'd upon so mistaken Grounds, that a bad one could not have a worse Face, nor be more weakly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended. Since therefore the Exceptions are so ill taken, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al so perplext and confus'd, it will be necessary briefly to state the Case itself; not with Design at present to settle the Point, but to shew she Weakness of the Authour.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Visitour</hi> pronounced the Sentence by the Advice of the most eminent <hi>Civilians</hi> of this Nation; and the Arguments which possibly induced him and them to that Opinion were, as I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, such as these.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:205037:20"/>I. Probably it was thought that an University, and every Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege therein was a mixt Body, partly <hi>lay,</hi> and partly <hi>Ecclesiastical,</hi> and in all other Nations entitled to the Privilege of both <hi>Forums.</hi> And if all other Universities, <hi>Generalia Studia</hi> and Colleges were by certain and established Rules of the Canon Law sometimes en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titled
<note place="bottom">a Ab in c. ex Literis.</note>, <hi>Ecclesiastical,</hi> often mixt
<note place="bottom">b <hi>Universitattem mixtum Sodaliti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um ac rerum mixturâ verius deceutiusque dici Ecclesiasticum, quàm profanum.</hi> Chopin. <hi>ex</hi> Gul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merio <hi>de Dom. Fr.</hi>
               </note> and seldom or never Lay Societies, it seem'd more reasonable to take the Standard of those in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> from other, many of them Protestant Colleges of the same Nature abroad, than from Hospitals and Lay Confraternities here at home. Especially since in all Charters and ancient Records of both Universities here in <hi>England</hi> their Members have usu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally been stiled
<note place="bottom">c 2. H. III. 5. Ed. III. 29. Ed. III. 14. H. VIII. <hi>See Prin. in</hi> 4. <hi>Iast. p.</hi> 36<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>
               <hi>Clerici;</hi> and it hath been expresly by Charter granted; that concerning them the Kings <hi>Prohibition</hi> should not lye. The Universities, as they now <hi>by Charter</hi> send Burgesses to Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and are in that respect <hi>lay;</hi> so have they anciently sent Deputies to the Councils, particularly to that of <hi>Constance,</hi> and have been admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red as Ecclesiastical Societies. And therefore tho' at Common Law, no Lay Person was capable of Tithes, but the King; Appropriations how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, were anciently made to Colleges, and that without Dispensation.</p>
            <p>And tho' in Colleges of <hi>Physitians</hi> or <hi>Lawyers,</hi> this Rule may admit of Exception; yet in Societies, as that of <hi>Exeter</hi> College, where most are actually in Orders, and others design'd for them; it is impossible that the <hi>end</hi> of the institution and the <hi>quality</hi> of the Persons con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curring, must not denominate the Society if not purely Ecclesiastical, at least not merely Lay. There is no more certain Rule in
<note place="bottom">d <hi>Panormitum</hi> c. <hi>ex</hi> lit. 16. <hi>Tus.</hi> t. 8. <hi>Con.</hi> 255. <hi>Mendo de jure. Acad. Alphonso d' Escobar.</hi> c. 21.</note> Canon Law, than that a Corporation cannot be merely secular; where the Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Ecclesiastical Persons equal the others, or exceed them.
<note place="bottom">e <hi>Covar.</hi> l. 2. <hi>Var.</hi> c. 20.8. <hi>Con. Alf. d' Esc.</hi> c. 21. <hi>Anton. Augustin. dict.</hi> l. 14. <hi>Epit. Jur. Can. l.</hi> 8. <hi>&amp;</hi> 9. <hi>Guim. de Pragm. Sanct. de Univer.</hi> 307.</note> And this Rule is still a greater Force, when the Society hath been erected and confirm'd by Ecclesiastical Authority.</p>
            <note n="†" place="bottom">
               <hi>See</hi> Vasq. <hi>de</hi> Prada <hi>de Jure Eccl.</hi> Coll. Salm. Over.</note>
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:205037:20"/>
            <p>
               <note place="bottom">a <hi>Hill.</hi> 18, <hi>&amp;</hi> 19. <hi>Car.</hi> 2.</note> In Dr. <hi>Patricks</hi> Case, <hi>Moreton</hi> holds, That most Colleges are Spiritual; <hi>Windham,</hi> That in some respect all Colleges to an elemmosynary end are Spiritual, in some Lay; and <hi>Keeling,</hi> That they were <hi>quodammodo</hi> Spiritual.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="bottom">b <hi>Hob.</hi> p. 122. 9 <hi>Eliz. Dyer</hi> 28. <hi>Coke</hi> 11. <hi>Rep.</hi> p. 99. See <hi>Sed.</hi> 71. <hi>Widrington</hi>'s Case.</note>
               <hi>A.</hi> 9. &amp; 10. <hi>Eliz. Mich.</hi> It was adjudg'd by all the Judges, <hi>per op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inionem omnium Justitiariorum utrius{que} Banci &amp; Capitalis Baronis Sacca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rii;</hi> that Trinity College in <hi>Cambridge</hi> was <hi>in some respects</hi> Spiritual: and within the Statute of 1 and 2 <hi>Phil.</hi> and <hi>Ma.</hi> which make good devises to Spiritual Corporations.</p>
            <p>And therefore Colleges, tho' not merely Ecclesiastical, yet out of a just caution, are excepted out of the Statute of <hi>Chanteries.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="bottom">c See <hi>Azeved.</hi> l. 10. n. 26. tit. 1. l. 4. &amp; l. 1. n. 3. tit. 18. l. 9.</note>
               <hi>Collegia instituta pro sustentatione studentium pauperum &amp; aliorum Egenorum sunt loca pia; &amp; gaudent Privilegiis Ecclesiae &amp; de Juris<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictione Ecclesiasticâ &amp; si sint institutu seu erecta Authoritate Ecclesia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stica non solum sunt sola pia sed etiam Religosa.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It was laid down then probably upon these or the like Authorities, that an University was not merely a <hi>Lay Corporation;</hi> and that Colleges being parts of the Body, and Coporations within a Corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, were of the same nature as the whole.</p>
            <p n="2">2. If the Body then that was to be visited, was mixt: It was presum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that a mixt Jurisdiction, as sufficient for the redress of all Enormi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties therein was lodg'd in the <hi>sole</hi> Visitours thereof; and this more espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially if the Person, from whom the Authority was deriv'd, could grant such Power; and the Offences, that were to be punished by the Visitour, could not be enquir'd into without it; and the Statutes (as is already prov'd) by plain and express words did convey and warrant it.</p>
            <p>Now the Visitation which is an enquiry into several Breaches, not only of the Law of the Land; but of Ecclesiastical Laws, and as in this case into <hi>Heresy,</hi> can hardly be perform'd without the concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent assistance of Ecclesiastical Jurisdiction. And therefore when <hi>Ordinaries</hi> are empower'd to enquire into the Foundation, Erection, and Governance of <hi>Hospitals,</hi> which are matters at first sight appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Lay and Secular;
<note place="bottom">d <hi>St. H.</hi> 5.1.</note> they are commanded to make Correction, and Reformation thereupon, after the Laws of <hi>Holy Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:205037:21"/>
            <p>
               <note place="bottom">a See <hi>VV.</hi> 2. c. 43. <hi>Coke</hi> 2. <hi>instit.</hi> 465, See <hi>Mendo</hi> l. 1. q. 26.</note> Not only the <hi>Judices Academiarum,</hi> but the <hi>Conservatores</hi> too a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad that represent the Visitours there; and the <hi>Conservatores</hi> of the <hi>Templars</hi> in <hi>England</hi> had always a mixt Jurisdiction.</p>
            <p>And therefore says <hi>Mendo, Visitatores</hi> [of <hi>Colleges] Episcoporum po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testatem promulgandi censuras habent; quâ si carerent, vis plurima eis de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficeret ad exequendum ea, quae expedire judicantur. De Jure Acad. D.</hi> 7. And so anciently in all Religious Houses which consisted most of Lay Members, and in the Visitation of them. <hi>Caenobitica Visitatorum censura ad Abates pertinet. [Dec. de Reg. c.</hi> 8. <hi>Chop. Monasticoon,</hi> l. 1.</p>
            <p>My Lord <hi>Coke</hi> thinks the <hi>Ecclesiastical Law</hi> proper to be us'd by a <hi>Visitor</hi> of all Societies founded in <hi>Liberâ Eleemosyna.</hi> Coke 1. Instit. 96. And this Power seem'd more necessarily lodg'd in the <hi>Visitonr;</hi> because it is evident,
<note place="bottom">b See <hi>Quarrant. v. exemptio.</hi> 6. <hi>H.</hi> 7.14. <hi>Zerol</hi> 2. <hi>part.</hi> 60. <hi>Balth. And. de Equitibus Hierosolymita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis. Gratian. disp. For.</hi> c. 870.</note> that those Fraternities whether <hi>Religious</hi> or <hi>Lay,</hi> that were once exempted from their <hi>Ordinaries,</hi> were immediately made subject to their <hi>Visitor;</hi> and the one Power was design'd to to supply the loss of the other.</p>
            <p>It is plain that a College is within 2 <hi>H.</hi> 5.1. Now then, if without a private appointment, it should be visitable, as some think, by the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary of the place; or as the better opinion is, it should fall into the bulk of the University, and be subject to the Chancellours Visitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; in both these Cases, it would be visited especially in <hi>Ecclesiasti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal</hi> Causes, as the <hi>Statute</hi> appoints, according to <hi>Holy Laws</hi> of the <hi>Church;</hi> because both Persons confessedly have Ecclesiastical Juris<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction. And therefore it seem'd not reasonable to suppose that a Visitour of a College <hi>ex institutione,</hi> vested with Ecclesiastical Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority by the Statutes, should have less Jurisdiction, that one who <hi>ex provisione legis,</hi> was call'd in to supply the want of him.</p>
            <p>As to the Grant it is plain, That the King can exempt any place from Jurisdiction of the <hi>Ordinary,</hi> and subject it to another <hi>Ecclesiasti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal</hi> or <hi>Episcopal</hi> Jurisdiction. <hi>Co.</hi> 5.1.4. <hi>Cok.</hi> 5.9.10.14. <hi>Dav. Com.</hi> 73. <hi>H.</hi> 1. <hi>Jac. B. R. Rot.</hi> 601. <hi>Rolls Ab.</hi> 341, 10. <hi>H.</hi> 7.18.</p>
            <p>If then Ecclesiastical Jurisdiction be necessary for the Visitour of a mixt Corporation; especially in Causes originally of Ecclesiastical
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:205037:21"/>Conusance; it must be presum'd that the Kings Grant to the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, for constituting a Visitour gave him Authority likewise of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veying to him such Powers which were necessarily incident to his Office. The King now enjoys the same Ecclesiastical Powers in this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as the Popeonce did; and in all other Countries it is own'd, That the <hi>mixt</hi> Jurisdiction is cast upon <hi>Abbots</hi> and other <hi>Visitors,</hi> not by Designation or Grant of the Pope, bat by the necessity of their Office. [<hi>Barb. de Jure Eccl.</hi> l. 1 c. 17. <hi>Suarez. de Rel.</hi> l. 1. <hi>Sanchez in summ.</hi> l 5]</p>
            <p>And lastly since the Governours of the University have always ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercised a mixt Jurisdiction; and the Charter of <hi>Exeter</hi> College entitles them to the same Customs, as the University; it seem'd reasonable to suppose that the Visitour of a College had claim in his small Sphere to the same Rights and Liberties, as the Chancellour in the University. <hi>Cum Collegia sint partes &amp; membra Academiae frunntur iisdem priuilegis quibus ea fungitur, praeter alia specialia, quae ipsis sunt concessa. [Mendo. p.</hi> 25.</p>
            <p>And this presumption is the stronger, because in other Colleges, as well as <hi>Exeter,</hi> the Founders, relying on these Reasons, and on this Authority have expresly granted to their Visitour the use of Ecclesiasti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Censures: especially since I find that the Visitors in <hi>H.</hi> 8's time, in the University, tho not impowered by express words of Commission us'd to punish the Members thereof by <hi>Ecclesiastical</hi> Censures, as well as <hi>Temporal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. If The Body was <hi>mixt,</hi> and a <hi>mixt</hi> Jurisdiction was lodg'd in the <hi>Visitor;</hi> Then the Cause of the Sentence it self being originally of Ecclesiastical Connusance, seem'd properly to direct the <hi>Visitor</hi> to the Use and Exercise of that Power. Heresie was chiefly chargd against him, and fully prov'd; the Contumacy receives its Nature from the Crime, and when the Principal whereupon it grew, was a Matter Spiritual; the Punishment of it is of the same <hi>Forum,</hi> and the Censures that enforce that Penalty, must and ought to be Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clesiastical: For <hi>Cujus Juris est principale ejusdem Juris erit acces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sorium. Bract.</hi> l. 5. c. 2. fol. 401. [See also <hi>Hankford</hi>'s <hi>Opinion,</hi> 2 <hi>H.</hi> 4.15.] And Ecclesiastical Process is allow'd not only <hi>in Causis Spiritualibus,</hi> but <hi>in Spiritualitati annexis,</hi> Bract. <hi>l.</hi> 5.</p>
            <p>And it is a Rule in the Register, 53. <hi>b. Ʋbi cognitio causae principa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis ad forum Ecclesiasticum pertinet; &amp; ejus accessorium pertinere de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet, [Dennis</hi> Case. <hi>Cro. Car.</hi> 115.]</p>
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:205037:22"/>
            <p>And therefore as Excommunication may be for <hi>Defamation</hi> and <hi>Perjury,</hi> so it may be us'd likewise for <hi>Costs and Expences</hi> adjudg'd which however <hi>lay</hi> in themselves are the Accessories and Dependen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of those Causes.
<note n="*" place="bottom">
                  <hi>Fitz. Tit. Prot. M.</hi> 4. <hi>H.</hi> 3.</note> For as <hi>Perjury,</hi> tho plainly in its Nature of Ecclefiastical Conusance, if it arose upon a Temporal Contract or Cause, is not triable in the Spiritual Court; so much more <hi>Depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation</hi> (which is neither of it self Temporal or Spiritual, but un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>determin'd) becomes an Ecclesiastical or Secular Purishment in respect of the Cause for which, and of the <hi>Forum</hi> in which it is inflicted.</p>
            <p>I have offer'd these Reasons with all submission, not entring into the merits of the Cause; but laying down the probable Motives and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducements to that Sentence: If a Bishop hath in every place Power of Excommunication in <hi>foro animae,</hi> and if he hath mixt Jurisdiction in the College according to to the Canon Law; and the Laws of the Land, he may then by Law inflict the Sentence; If he hath not such Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, The Custom of all other Universities and Colleges, the Nature of the Cause and of his own Power, the Practice of Visitors here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore, and the plain Words of the Founder have <hi>misled</hi> him. But howsoever the Cause be determin'd by those learned Judges that it now lies before: Certain it is, that as the Visitor in this Case could not have a more <hi>rude,</hi> so he could not have a <hi>weaker</hi> Adversary. For whether the Bishop had ecclefiastical Jurisdiction or not, he could nevertheless, as Visitor, take away the Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Right. To excommunicate for <hi>Rent</hi> is a forreign and idle suppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sal; for Heresie is not <hi>materia laica;</hi> and therefore if the Authority was mistaken, the Cause however was Ecclesiastical. Nor is there any agreement between a Mannor and a College, between a <hi>mixt</hi> and a <hi>lay</hi> Corporation: As much is the Disparity between a Lord and a Visitor, where one hath connusance only of <hi>Temporal</hi> Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, the other hath power to enquire into <hi>Ecclesiastical</hi> Offences. There is an apparent difference between <hi>two</hi> Jurisdictions and a <hi>mixt</hi> Jurisdiction; <hi>two</hi> Jurisdictions may occasionally and by acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent be lodg'd in the same Person; as in the Bishop of <hi>Durham;</hi> but a <hi>mixt</hi> Jurisdiction, as arising from the Nature of the Cause, is always, not by chance but <hi>necessity</hi> vested in one Man, as in the <hi>Chancellors</hi> of both Universities. Now in one Cause the Original of
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:205037:22"/>the Powers is wholly accidental, and therefore they ought not to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfere and be mixt; but in the other, that which was the reason of mixing the Jurisdiction, is as strong for maintaining them <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>distinguish'd, and subservient</hi> to each other. In one Case it is a Rule <hi>Quando duo Jura concurrunt, aequum est ac si essent in diversis;</hi> in the other, <hi>Qui utroque Jure potest facere cundem actum utroque Jure fecisse videtur;</hi> and therefore the Chancellor of <hi>Oxford</hi> having a <hi>mixt</hi> Jurisdiction, can by Charter, confirm'd by Act of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, excommunicate the Mayor for breaking the Priviledges of the University. <hi>Coveney</hi>'s Case makes nothing against this Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion; for it is plain, that the Matter of the Deprivation, <hi>i. e.</hi> the <hi>cause</hi> of it was purely temporal; the Crime was not <hi>Heresie,</hi> but <hi>not entring into Orders;</hi> the resolution that was there taken is clear; for it cannot be pretended that an Appeal in that Case lay from the Visitor upon <hi>Stat.</hi> 24. and 25. <hi>H.</hi> VIII. as upon a Spiritual Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, and as from a Court merely Ecclesiastical; and upon that Ground the Opinion was confirm'd in Dr. <hi>Lewis</hi>'s Case. How far there is ground for a <hi>Prohibition</hi> therefore in this Case, I will not dispute; but, tho the Excommunication should be allow'd to be void; tho the <hi>alibi</hi> in the Statute hath been already drawn into its full extent, yet I am confident, there it but one Man in <hi>England,</hi> whose Opinion we need not much value, that will dream of a <hi>Praemunire.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>3. As to the Vacancy of Dr. <hi>Hern</hi>'s Place.</head>
               <p>That he may refute some what, it is usual with this Author to make Objections himself, which no body else ever mention'd; and then to shew his Skill in answer in them. For first he proves in Dr. <hi>Hern</hi>'s Case, that <hi>Obsequium Officium &amp; Exercitium</hi> cannot extend to an Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siastical Benefice; no, nor was it ever pretended that they did; but I hope <hi>Ecclesiasticum Beneficium,</hi> in the same Statute will reach to it. Benefices indeed oftentimes are not reputed inconsistent with Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowships, according to the intrinsick, but an estimated Value. The real Value is usually unsetled, and as depending upon Casualties, is <hi>floating</hi> and <hi>uncertain;</hi> therefore the incompatibility of a Living ought to be taken from fixt and certain <hi>Rates,</hi> and those appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on publick Record. The Kings Books, 'tis always own'd, are
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:205037:23"/>such <hi>Regia Monumenta;</hi> and are not the Acts of Parliament as much <hi>Publica Monumenta?</hi> And is not, in the Letter of the Law, as well as in the intendment of the Legislator, the latter as good Evidence of the Value as the former? Now then, since an Annuity of 100<hi>l.</hi> is, besides many other Advantages, setled by Act of Parliament on S. <hi>Anns;</hi> is not this in the <hi>nature</hi> of the thing, as inconsistent as one of <hi>Eight?</hi> And hath it not a stated Value different from the intrinsick? And dothnot this appear in the most publick Records of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom? And is it not then ridiculous to say that the Living is not tax'd at 100<hi>l. per Ann.</hi> but the Parish is tax'd to make it 100 <hi>l. per Ann.</hi> Nor can any Man that knew the Statutes of other Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leges in both Universities pretend, that this Precedent, however determin'd, can be of so universal influence. For since most of the Colleges in both Universities were founded before the making of the Records in the <hi>First-Fruits Office;</hi> All his Arguments for them that enforce a reference to those Records only, not by equitable Construction, but express Words, prove nothing but his Ignorance in the Chronology of those famous Foundations.</p>
               <p>Thus much I have said for Argument only, since the <hi>Author</hi> after a tedious Discourse, hath as usually not touch'd the Point in question; And tho indeed his Reasons which have been shown to be very weak, would have tempted a Man to be of another Opinion; yet I freely confess, that as to all Livings which are at all rated in the <hi>Kings Books;</hi> and were, if not rated, then in being; The Statute seems naturally to refer it self to those Books only, and the <hi>Publick Records</hi> there mention'd may, (and as I think, and always thought) in strictness of Law ought to be ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally taken under that limited and restrain'd Interpretation. But, as to all <hi>new</hi> Livings not then in being, and consequently not rated in their Books, since erected, and reduc'd to a setled Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue by Act of Parliament. I take the Provision for them to be <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus Omissus</hi> in the Statutes, and which by equitable Construction, and by a competent Judge, <hi>reducendus est ad expressum.</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I further conceive, that the <hi>Vice Chancellor</hi> having no Power of expounding the Statutes, did well declare, That the <hi>Fellowship</hi> and <hi>Benefice</hi> were not according to the Letter of the Statutes, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>consistent; and, that Dr. <hi>Bouchiers</hi> Opinion was at that time, in that place, well grounded: For the Statutes are to be observ'd,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:205037:23"/>
                  <hi>secundum planum &amp; grammaticalem sensum, Reservata duntaxat praed' Reverendo Patri &amp; Successoribus suis Episcopis Exon justa emergen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium ex iisdem Statutis dubior' interpretatione;</hi> and therefore the <hi>Vice-Chancellor</hi> who was only let in as an Arbitrator between the <hi>Rector</hi> and the <hi>Fellows,</hi> must be guided by the Letter of the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute; but the <hi>Visitor</hi> having always a power of interpreting the Statutes in his Visitation, and upon request, out of it, might law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully pursue the the well, intent, and plain design of the Law. And therefore since in his Judgment, and according to the plain intendment of the Legislator, now judicially declar'd, this was reduc'd to the other ordinary Cases express'd in the Statute; The Living was, and is plainly inconsistent with a Fellowship. And at first indeed the Cognizance of the Cause being not so properly a disagreement between <hi>Rector</hi> and <hi>Fellow,</hi> as a doubt arising from the Statute, ought not to have been brought to the <hi>Vice-Chancellor,</hi> but before the <hi>Visitor;</hi> and therefore the Matter being never setled before a proper Judge, was now first judicially mov'd and determin'd; I am well inform'd by Letter from Dr. <hi>Boucher,</hi> and it appears in his Opinion it self, that he did at that time ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vise an appeal to the <hi>Visitor;</hi> and therefore the Reflection of this <hi>Author</hi> upon him, upon this account, is as false, as is it rude and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingenous.</p>
               <p>As to his Residence it is plain, that the reason of a <hi>Fellows</hi> ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence from the College beyond 50 days must be <hi>Mors seu gravis infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitus parentum,</hi> or <hi>causa promotionis,</hi> and then a <hi>tempus certum</hi> must be appointed; and leave must be given <hi>habito respectu ad Causas Personas intervalla locorum, &amp; circumstantias ejusmodi.</hi> When a Fellow is then in hopes of preferment; this Statute allows absence for attainment of it, and doth not limit the time, but proposes some Rules for discretionary Limitation. But when he <hi>is advanc'd,</hi> and hath for some Years had quiet Possession of a Parsonage; Then it is this Gentlemans Opinion, that <hi>Causa promotionis</hi> signifies the enjoyment of a Benefice, and that an indeterminate leave, perhaps for Life, may be granted. The <hi>Author</hi> of the Account is sworn to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend the Privileges of the University, and hath, and will perform his Oath. But in the mean time he knows that the <hi>Worthy Members</hi> of that <hi>learned Body</hi> desire not to elude the Statutes of their <hi>Founders,</hi> by so scandalous and senseless <hi>Evasions;</hi> and that there are very few of them,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:205037:24"/>and those but in one College that will in this Case be more pleas'd with the <hi>fair Dealing</hi> of their new <hi>pretended Advocate;</hi> than they are hitherto satisfied with his Learning and Sense.</p>
               <p>If then the Statutes will not excuse his Absence from the College; it is pretended that the Law will discharge him from Residence from his Parsonage. The Question is, whether Dr. <hi>Herne</hi> having a Parish in <hi>London,</hi> and being oblig'd to reside upon it, four Parts of five in a Year, can beyond that allow'd time of Absence be resident in <hi>Oxford.</hi> He answers, That Dr. <hi>Hern</hi> is excus'd from Residence, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing the Act of Parliament that enjoyns it, because by a sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sequent act, 1 <hi>Jac.</hi> 2. The <hi>Rector</hi> is to have an House built at the Charge of the Parish; and therefore, till that be built, <hi>Non-resi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance,</hi> as involuntary, is no Crime; and in this Point he says, The Law is very clear. The <hi>Author</hi> was impos'd upon by a Case or two explanatory of 21 <hi>H.</hi> 8. It was doubted whether that Act oblig'd a Man to Residence only, in his Parish, or more particularly in the Parsonage House. If there was no House for the Parson, then the Incumbent is excus'd from that part of the Law which is impossible. For <hi>impotentia excusat legem;</hi> But as there is no im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>possibility for Residence in General, tho the House be not built, so neither do the Cases warrant or excuse <hi>Non-Residence.</hi> [See <hi>Goodals</hi> Case, <hi>Coke</hi> 6. <hi>p.</hi> 21. See <hi>Cr. Eliz. p.</hi> 590, 591.] And the <hi>Canon Law,</hi> which was the Ground of those Reports is clear in the Point, that he ought to live in the Vicinage, and not at forty seven Miles distance from his Parish in <hi>Oxford.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>4. That the <hi>Visitor</hi> hath no Power by Statute of Suspending the Fellows <hi>ab Officio &amp; Beneficio.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Upon this Head the <hi>Author</hi> declaims much, and long, and Dreams that the Suspension <hi>ab Officio especially,</hi> is so far from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing warranted by Statute, that under the Pain of <hi>Perjury</hi> it cannot be submitted to by a Fellow. It would be easie to prove, that his Penalty being less then <hi>Expulsion,</hi> may without express Words
<note place="bottom">r
<p>
                        <hi>Barbosa de Offic. Par. p.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 8. <hi>n.</hi> 41. <hi>Debet Residere Parochus in domo Parochiai, ipsa deficiente, residere debet in domo aliqua quae sit intra Parochiae limites, &amp; ita Ecclesia contigua ut commode passet Ecclesia deservire.</hi> See <hi>Cock. de Jure &amp; Just. p.</hi> 67.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Parochus non habans commodam habitationem in Parochia dispensatus est ut possit in loco</hi> vicino. <hi>residere Sess. Trid.</hi> 23. <hi>p.</hi> 216.</p>
                  </note> Statutes be legally inflicted by the <hi>Visitor. Putting out of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons,</hi>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:205037:24"/>is a <hi>Suspension à Beneficio,</hi> and of that, if they were worth any thing, Dr. <hi>Bury</hi> hath afforded us Precedents: Other Reasons might be suggested, were it not a very convincing one, that the Statnte it self, which this <hi>Gentleman</hi> might have read, expresly enjoys this Punishment. <hi>Eliamsi ad</hi> privationem <hi>aut</hi> amotionem <hi>Rectoris, Subrectoris vel alterius cujuscun{que}</hi> ab Administratione <hi>sua vel</hi> Officio <hi>procedat.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>5. Whether the <hi>Visitor</hi> ought to have been Judge in his own Cause, or pronounc'd for his own Jurisdiction.</head>
               <p>It is said indeed, that is against Natural Equity to make a Man Judge in his own Cause, and that an Act of Parliament that should establish such a Practice, would be void: And this General Maxim, grossly mistaken, and misapply'd, hath impos'd upon this Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man. A Man that is not Judge of his own Cause, may, and every where does pronounce for his own Jurisdiction, and over-rule the Exceptions of the Criminal. When his Property is concern'd, a Judge must withdraw, but not when the Authority of his Court is question'd. <hi>Quilibet Judex potest</hi> pronunciare pro seipso, <hi>quia licet illud non det ei jurisdictionem; tamen constituit ipsum in quasi possessione Jurisdictionis: propter quod habet justam cognitionem, &amp; pronunciationem.</hi> [Abb. in c. cum Ordinem in fine de resumpt. Mart. de Jurisd. c. 4. p. 2. &amp;c. 18. n. 8.]</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>That the Concurrence of the Fellows to the <hi>Rectors</hi> Expulsion was not Statutable.</head>
               <p>If the others had appear'd, they had not been suspended, and then they had been proper Judges; since they did not appear, and were justly punish'd, they became <hi>Participes Crimnis,</hi> &amp; <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonae Inhabiles,</hi> and consequently in Law and Reason, as to any Exercise of Jurisdiction, were reputed <hi>absent.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He pursued therefore the Statute strictly, and the Expulsion of Dr. <hi>Bury</hi> was not more just in it self, than legally carried on. When those Fellows that had opposs'd the Jurisdiction of the <hi>Visitor,</hi> were statutably suspended <hi>ab Officio;</hi> then it is very weak to talk of the Bishops taking in others, when the Statute had devolv'd the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority on those that were in place nearest to them. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the consent of no others could be had, than of such as were not incapacitated to give a legal Concurrence.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:205037:25"/>
               <head>Lastly, the Contumacy is no statutable Cause of Expulsion, and if it were ought in the Case of the <hi>Fellows</hi> as well as the <hi>Rector,</hi> to receive the same Punishment from the <hi>Visitor.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>If a Man had not been us'd to <hi>like</hi> arguing thro the Book, he would be surpriz'd at the last Exception in the close of it. <hi>Contumacy</hi> is not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited as one of the Crimes for which the <hi>Rector</hi> might be expelld, and therefore is no good Cause of Deprivation; so that if a <hi>Rector</hi> when an <hi>Heretick</hi> and <hi>Incontinent</hi> made a <hi>weak</hi> Defence, he <hi>might</hi> be depriv'd, if he made <hi>none,</hi> he <hi>must</hi> be safe and secur'd.</p>
               <p>Contumacy upon a Charge includes the Offence it self, and aggravates it, it amounts in Construction of Law to a <hi>Confession</hi> of the <hi>Crime,</hi> and to a <hi>Contempt</hi> of the <hi>Judge;</hi> and any Court that hath no Power of punishing it, hath in effect no Power at all. The Statute says, <hi>Ostendantur ei detecta, quibus si non possit rationabiliter &amp; honeste respondere, amoveatur:</hi> and I leave this <hi>Gentleman</hi> to prove that a refusal of appearance before a <hi>proper</hi> Judge, is a sufficient Answer to a Charge</p>
               <p>As to the second Exception, it is clear, that the same <hi>Contumacy</hi> is not only respected in Law but the ground of it. When the charge is different; the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tumacy</hi> may be the <hi>same,</hi> but neither the <hi>Crime</hi> is, nor the <hi>Punishment</hi> ought to be <hi>equal.</hi> That which bears nearest resemblance to <hi>Contumacy</hi> in Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Law is <hi>Outlawry.</hi> Outlawry in <hi>Trespass,</hi> is no Forfeiture of Land, as Outlawry in <hi>Felony</hi> is; the <hi>not-appearing</hi> in both Cases is the <hi>cause</hi> of Outlawry, yet the Force of the Outlawry shall be esteem'd according to the heinousnes of the Offence, which was the Ground and Foundation of the Process. His Lordship therefore had not equal Reason to expel the <hi>Fellows</hi> as the <hi>Rector,</hi> but wonders much that in the <hi>Case of Exeter College,</hi> the greatest exce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption against his Proceedings should be his tenderness to the <hi>Fellows</hi> thereof.</p>
               <p>Thus the whole State of this Controversy hath been enquir'd into and set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, and thereby not only the <hi>immaterial</hi> Objections, which have already been made, are <hi>answered,</hi> but all <hi>future Exceptions</hi> are prevented. The Powers of a <hi>Visitor,</hi> as has been prov'd, are general, and not more fixt by private appointment, than ascertain'd by Law: <hi>Appeals</hi> from this <hi>Domestick</hi> Judge are by Statute taken away, bet no recourse to him, either in this or any other <hi>College,</hi> hath ever been deny'd. It is evident then, that the <hi>Commission</hi> of <hi>Appeal</hi> was rightly granted, and it is equally clear, that the <hi>Visitation</hi> has been <hi>Statuable</hi> and <hi>Legal,</hi> and if (as is now plain) the <hi>Jurisdiction</hi> of the Judge was <hi>certain,</hi> and the <hi>Process warrantable,</hi> none of the Adversaries themselves will dispute the Justice of the Sentence.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="answer">
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:205037:25"/>
            <head>AN ANSWER TO THE Account Examin'd.</head>
            <p>SInce the <hi>Account Examin'd</hi> is a Panegyrick on Dr. <hi>Bury,</hi> it is easie to discover the Author, and to find out the only Man in <hi>England,</hi> that would write well on that Subject. The <hi>Answer</hi> to it, as anticipated by M. <hi>Colmlr,</hi> will here be very short; especially, since the whole Pamphlet is at best only a bold denial of his own Crimes; and is oftentimes a Confession of the Charge. The Author of the <hi>Account</hi> had published nothing against him, but what was warran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by Authentick Vouchers; and it is not his fault if the faithful and exact History of a Mans Life, becomes the severest Satyr against him. Malice is ridiculously charg'd up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Author against a Person wholly unknown: He knows no more of him, than of <hi>Socinus,</hi> or <hi>Sandius;</hi> but that his Principles are fully as bad; and his Learning much less. The little immaterial Exceptions, that are taken to the <hi>Account,</hi> are all false; but would for the most part be whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly impertinent to the purpose, if true. The great Incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stancy of which the Author of the <hi>Account</hi> is guilty, is that the Enormous Crimes of the Rector, are sometimes made the Cause of the Visitation; and sometimes the Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:205037:26"/>of them is gloried in, as the Effect of it. The notorious Scandal was the Cause of the Visitation; and the Discovery of the Crimes by legal Proof, was the Result of it. The suspicion of <hi>Heresie</hi> and <hi>Incontinency</hi> was vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, and occasion'd the <hi>Visitours</hi> Enquiry: The Proof of the Charge was plain, and brought on the Decree of the <hi>University;</hi> Crimes may upon violent Presumptions be known before a Tryal; and yet the Tryal it self, and the Witnesses therein produc'd, must concur to the legal Convi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the Criminals.</p>
            <p n="1">1. As to the <hi>Naked Gospel,</hi> It hath already been censur'd and burnt; and after the Decree of that <hi>Learned</hi> and <hi>Judici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous</hi> Body upon so <hi>Infamous</hi> and <hi>Heretical</hi> a Book, it would be much more Prudence for him <hi>once more</hi> to recant his Tenets, than to defend them. For let his Friends of the <hi>Polonian</hi> Faith be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond Sea, know, That never any Decree was more unanimously sign'd, nor more willingly assented to by the Right Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend, and Reverend the Heads, and the worthy Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the whole University.</p>
            <p>The manner of Christs Generation was not the Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stion, but his Divinity: And it is a very extensive Charity indeed, that takes in all Christians, but at the same time excludes Jesus Christ. If those bold Assertions (as he says) fell from him through Heat; I believe the same warmth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued, when he took <hi>Ann Sparrow</hi> into his House; when he expell'd Mr. <hi>Colmar,</hi> and oppos'd the <hi>Visitour.</hi> When the Author calls <hi>Jesus Christ</hi> a Crucify'd Vagabond, he says, That <hi>he personated an Infidel;</hi> and the Vizard that then was put on, was not, I believe in the whole Book taken off.
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:205037:26"/>If none under a Dean may read <hi>Socinians</hi> Books; it seems however, that one under that Degree may <hi>write</hi> them; and the Copies of the <hi>Naked Gospel,</hi> if fitted for Deans only, ought not to have amounted to 500. However, The Gentleman, I see, quotes Cantons which he never read; nor can it be well expected, That he should be acquainted with the Rules and Orders of a Church; who denies the Chief Articles of her Faith.</p>
            <p>As to his <hi>Immortality:</hi> The Affidavits that were there made in the Visitation were my guides, and afterwards his own Confession hath confirm'd most of those Depositions. He boasts much of his Loyalty, which it is not my business to deny: The charge is <hi>Heresie, Incontinence and Bribery,</hi> and the Plea is; that he is not guilty of <hi>Treason.</hi> I am glad indeed that he is free from any one Crime, but at the same time it is hard, that a Man shall be excus'd for <hi>Crucifying</hi> his Saviour, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause he is <hi>Caesars Friend.</hi> It is not my business to look into his Life: The History of the Visitation I have strictly pursued, and even in that out of respect to his Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter, omitted a very scandalous part of the Charge. It is the disingenuous task of other Men to publish <hi>false</hi> and <hi>surreptitious</hi> Affidavits: What I have at any time set forth hath been so clearly, and judicially prov'd; and wholly made out, that after all his Subterfuges, the Criminal himself dares <hi>not</hi> disavow it. For doth he deny that being then Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vicechancour <hi>inaudità perfidiâ</hi> (which are the words of the Decree) he oblig'd <hi>Litchfield</hi> by colour of his Authority to print the <hi>Naked Gospel?</hi> Is he the Author of that Heretical Treatise or not? did he call his Saviour <hi>Crucify'd Vagabond,</hi> or will
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:205037:27"/>he deny the charge? Doth he not own that he sat at St. <hi>Atha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nasius</hi> Creed? That he sold the Places and Offices of the College; and was guilty of Bribery and Extortion? In short, there is no part of the Charge, that is totally disavow'd but Adultery, and yet that crime too as it was clearly made out in Visitation; so since by supplemental Evidence is confirm'd. And therefore it is left to the World to judge, how far the Church, and Nation in general are oblig'd to the seasonable care of the University for censuring and burning that Bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sphemous and Heretical Book; and to the Right Reverend the Bishop of <hi>Exeter</hi> for expelling the Author of it.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:205037:27"/>
            <p>A COPY OF THE PROCEEDINGS OF Dr. <hi>MASTER</hi> UPON The Commission of Appeal.</p>
            <list>
               <pb facs="tcp:205037:28"/>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:205037:28"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>Reverendo admodum in Christo Patri ac Dom. Dom.</hi> JONATHAN <hi>Permissione Divinâ</hi> Exon. <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piscopo Collegii</hi> Exon. <hi>in Ʋniversitate</hi> Oxon. <hi>Patrono &amp; Visitatori Ordinario,</hi> Edvardus Master <hi>Legum Doct. Vicar. vester in Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tualibus Generalis &amp; Comissar. vester in hac Parte special. constitut. omnimodas Obedientiam &amp; Reverentiam Paternitati vestrae Reverend. Tenore praesentium innotescimus, significamus &amp; certificamus, quae Vigore &amp; Virtute Commissionis vestrae mihi in hac Parte fact. &amp; direct. &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit. cum Reverentiâ praesentat. &amp; tradit. pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessum fuit, &amp; est prout sequitur. (viz.)</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Die Sabbati (viz.)</hi> Vicesimo secundo die Mensis <hi>Martii,</hi> Anno Dom. (Stylo <hi>Angliae</hi>) 1689. inter horas nonam &amp; undecimam ante Merid. ejusdem diei in Capella Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legii <hi>Exon.</hi> in Universitate <hi>Oxon.</hi> coram ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerabili &amp; egregio viro <hi>Edvardo Master</hi> Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gum Doctore Reverendi admodum Patris Domini <hi>Jonathanis</hi> Permissione Divinâ <hi>Exon.</hi> Episcopi, Patroni &amp; Visitatoris Collegii <hi>Exon.</hi> predict. Ordinarii Commissario vestro judicialiter seden. in praesentia mei <hi>Johannis Greeneway</hi> Notarii Publici subscript. in hac P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rte specialiter assumpti.</item>
            </list>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:205037:29"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Negotium appellationis promotum per</hi> Jacobum Colmer <hi>Artis Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistrum Collegii Exon predict. Socium contra Doct.</hi> Bury, <hi>ejusdem Coll. Rectorem</hi> George Verman <hi>Coll. predict, Subrector &amp; alios &amp;c. Quibus Die hora &amp; Loco coram praefato ven. &amp; egregio Viro</hi> Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vardo Master <hi>Legum Doct. judicialiter seden. comparuit</hi> Thomas Wood <hi>Legum Bacc. ex parte Reverendi admodum in Christo Patris ac Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini Domini</hi> Jonathanis <hi>permissione divina Exon Episcopi Collegii Exon praedict. Patroni &amp; Visitatoris ordinarii exhibuit Literas Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>missionales ejusdem Reverendi Patris Patroni &amp; Visitatoris praedict. presato</hi> Edvardo Master <hi>Legum Doctori direct. quas eidem Ven. &amp; egregio Viro</hi> Edvardo Master <hi>debita cum Reverentia tradidit &amp; pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sentavit humiliter petens quatenus praefat.</hi> Edvardus Master <hi>onus Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutionis earundem Literarum Commissionalium in se assumere &amp; ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptare &amp; juxta vim formam tenorem &amp; effectum earundem procedere &amp; pro Jurisdictione sua seu potius vestra in hac parte decernere dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naretur quibus per eum debita simili reverentiâ receptis &amp; publice tunc &amp; ibid perlectis dictus</hi> Edvardus Master <hi>onus Executionis Literarum Commissionalium hujusmodi ob honorem &amp; Reverentiam di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cti Reverendi Patris Patroni &amp; Visitatoris Committen. &amp;c. In se assumpsit &amp; acceptavit &amp; procedend fore decrevit in hujusmodi negotio appellationis juxta &amp; secundum omnem vim formam tenorem &amp; effectum earundem &amp; Juris in hac parte exigentiam meque</hi> Jo. Greeneway <hi>No. Pub. in actorem scribam sive Reg. pro expeditione hujusmodi Negotii appellationis assumpsit tunc factâ trina preconi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zatione pro dict.</hi> Arthur Bury <hi>S. Th, Professor. Coll. praedict. Recto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re</hi> Georgio Verman <hi>Subrectore</hi> Ezra Cleveland, Thoma Lethbridge Richardo Hutchins, Benjamino Archer, Samuel Adams &amp; Philippo Thorne <hi>sociis Collegii Exon proedict. ad interessend. istis die hora &amp; Loco ultime citatis ad respondend. dicto</hi> Jacobo Colmer <hi>in hujus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modi Negotio appellationis comparuerunt Personaliter venerabilis Vir</hi> Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thur Bury <hi>S. T. P. Rector dicti Collegii necnon</hi> Georgius Verman <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rector ibid</hi> Ezra Cleeveland. Thomas Lethbridge, Richardus Hutch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ins &amp; Philippus Thorn <hi>sed</hi> Benjamin Archer <hi>&amp;</hi> Samuel Adams <hi>non comparuerunt quorum paenas Dominus reservavit in prox. Tunc compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruit</hi> Jacobus Colmer <hi>pars appellans &amp; constituit Magistrum</hi> Thomam Wood <hi>Legum Bacc in ejus legitimum procuratorem ad agend: &amp;c. quod statim in se acceptavit &amp; fecit se &amp;c. Tunc facta denuo trina praeconizatione pro dict.</hi> Benjamin Archer &amp; Samuel Adams <hi>eis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:205037:29"/>non comparen. &amp;c. dictus</hi> Wood <hi>in presentia Doctoris</hi> Bury Georgii Verman, Ezrae Cleeveland, Thomae Lethbridg, Richardi Hutchins &amp; Philippi Thorn <hi>comparen. &amp; in penam Contu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maciae dict</hi> Archer <hi>&amp;</hi> Adams <hi>absen. Loco Libelli exhibuit Protocol. appellationis quod Dom admisit quatenus de Jure &amp;c. De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inde dictus</hi> Wood <hi>exhibuit Inhibitionem &amp; Monitionem pro transmis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sione totius processus in hoc negotio habit &amp; fact. &amp; allegavit easdem fuisse &amp; esse debite execut. juxta Certificat. authentic. sub sigillo Officialitatis Berks factaque deinde trina preconizatione pro dict</hi> Archer <hi>&amp;c</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dams <hi>non comparen. Dominus in penam non comparen. &amp; in praesentia comparen. monuit eos ad introducend. processum in prima hujus causae instantia fact. &amp;c. post merid &amp; ulteriorem executionem dictae com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>missionis continuavit &amp; prorogavit ad publicam Cameram infradict Colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gium Exon. notorie situat. inter horam secundam &amp; quartam pome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid. hujus diei monitis partibus presen. ad tunc ibid interessend. &amp; in penam</hi> Archer <hi>&amp;</hi> Adams <hi>non comparend Cont. Cur. &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Eodem die inter horam Secund. &amp; quartam pomerid coram praefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to</hi> Edvardo Master <hi>Legum Doctore Commissario antedict in publica Camera in Collegio proed. pro Tribunal. seden. vocatis prius praefatis Doctore</hi> Bury, Georgio Verman, Ezra Cleeveland, Thom. Leth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridg, Richardo Hutchins &amp; Philippo Thorn <hi>factâque trina preconi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zatione pro dict</hi> Benj. Archer <hi>&amp;</hi> Samuel Adams <hi>eisque non comparen. comparuit</hi> Wood <hi>Procurator dict.</hi> Jacobi Colmer <hi>&amp; in praesentia di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor. Doctoris</hi> Bury, Georgii Verman, Ezrae Cleeveland, Thomae Lethbridg, Richardi Hutchins &amp; Philippi Thorn. <hi>Comparen. &amp; in penam Contumaciae dict.</hi> Archer &amp; Adams <hi>absen. petiit procedend. fore juxta formam retroactorum in praesentia dict. Doctoris</hi> Bury, Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orgii Verman, Thomae Lethbridg &amp; Philippi Thorn <hi>exhiben. scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum quoddam continens protestationes suas manibus suis propriis sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>script. &amp; attestat. quod petierunt admitti &amp; inactitari sic Incipiens</hi> in Visitatione <hi>Collegii Exon &amp;c. Et sic terminans privilegiis nostris hac ex parte intemeratis quod scriptum Dominus ad eorum peticionem admisit quatenus de Jure sit admittend. &amp; non aliter neque alio modo Interrogatis prius Magistris</hi> Ezra Cleeveland <hi>&amp;</hi> Rich. Hutchins <hi>du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obus ex Sociis dict. Colleg. Exon. Senior. an velint dict. script. sive Protestationem attestari sub manibus suis dict.</hi> Cleeveland <hi>&amp;</hi> Hutch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ins <hi>expresse renuncian. &amp; eidem non consentientibus. Tunc Dominus ad petitionem dict. Doctoris</hi> Bury <hi>reservavit potestatem subscribendi dict. Instrument dictis</hi> Archer &amp; Adams <hi>absentibus si eidem Instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:205037:30"/>subscribere voluerint cum venerint. Postea Dominus non ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stante protestatione proed. Doct.</hi> Bury, Georgii Verman, Thomae Lethbridg &amp; Philippi Thorn <hi>decrevit procedend. fore in hoc Negotie &amp; monuit dict. Doctorem</hi> Bury <hi>aliosque comparen. ad introducend. processum in hoc Negotio juxta Monitionem eis Judicialiter fact. eis ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro non introducentibus Dominus</hi> Wood <hi>accusavit Contumacias dictor. Doctoris</hi> Bury, Georgii Verman, Ezrae Cleeveland, Thomae Leth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridg, Richardo Hutchins &amp; Philippi Thorn <hi>in non transmittendo vel exhibendo processum in primâ hujus pretensae causae instantiâ habitae &amp; fact. &amp; petiit sententiam ferri &amp;c. dictis vero Doctore</hi> Bury, Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orgio Verman, Thoma Lethbridg &amp; Philippo Thorn <hi>alleg. quod virtute Stat, Collegii praed. processum in causa amotionis vel expulsionis tene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>antur procedere summarie &amp; de plano &amp; sine strepitu Judiciali eaque de causa nullum processum in Scriptis habuisse aut habere nec proinde posse exhibere nec ullum Stat. violasse. Tunc factâ denuo trina pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conisatione pro dict.</hi> Archer <hi>&amp;</hi> Adams <hi>eisque non comparen. Dominus</hi> Wood <hi>in penam eorum contumac. &amp; in praesentia comparen. obtulit Sententiam definitivam quam petiit admitti ferri legi &amp; promulgari sed Dominus ad petitionem dictor. Doctoris</hi> Bury, Georgii Verman, Thomae Lethbridg &amp; Philippi Thorn <hi>continuavit &amp; prorogavit ul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teriorem expeditionem hujusmodi Commissionis &amp; finalem auditionem hujusmodi Causae in Diem Martis prox. inter horas Secund. &amp; Quart. pomerid, ejufdem diei hoc in loco Monitis partibus tunc praesentibus &amp;c. Cont. Certificatorio &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Postea Die Martis</hi> (viz) <hi>Vicesimo Quinto Die Mensis Martii An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no Dom.</hi> 1690. <hi>Inter horas tertiam &amp; quartam pomerid. in hac parte Assignatas in publica Camera Colleg. Exon. praed. coram proefato venerabili &amp; egregio Viro</hi> Edvardo Master <hi>Leg. Dict. Com. antedict. pro tribunal. seden. in praesentia mei</hi> Jo. Greeneway Not. Pub.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Quibus, &amp;c. factâ trina praeconizatione pro dict' Doctor'</hi> Bury, Georgio Verman, Ezra Cleeveland, Thom' Lethbridge, Richardo Hutchins, Benjamino Archer, Samuel' Adams <hi>&amp;</hi> Philippo Thorne <hi>Comparuerunt &amp; Exhibuerunt Scriptum quoddam de novo continens protestationes suas manibus suis subscript' &amp; attestatas (except'</hi> Cleeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land <hi>&amp;</hi> Hutchins) <hi>quod petiterunt admitti &amp; inactitari sic incipiens In visitatione Collegii Exon' Et sic terminans protestantes irritum fore quicquid contra Acta nostra Statutum fuerit. Quod Scriptum petierunt admitti &amp;c. Dominus admisit quatenus de Jure sit admittend. &amp; non
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:205037:30"/>aliter neque alio modo: Tunc Dominus pronunciavit pro Jurisdictione suae &amp;c. Et</hi> Wood <hi>petiit processum coram eisdem fact. juxta Monicionem introducend. fore &amp;c. Qui responderunt se non habere alium proces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sum quam qui Protestationi hac Die dat. annex. est Moniti deinde ad proband. dict. processum ad petitionem</hi> Wood <hi>responderunt se non te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neri Dom. judican. probare sufficere sibiipsis liquid. &amp; verum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tunc dictus</hi> Wood <hi>obtulit &amp; porrexit Dom. judican. sententiam definitivam pro Parte sua, quam petiit admitti, ferri, legi &amp; promulga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri in praesentia dictorum Doctoris</hi> Bury, Georgii Verman, Ezrae Clevc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Thomae Lethbridge, Richardi Hutchins, Philippi Thorne, Ben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jamin Archer <hi>&amp;</hi> Samuel Adams <hi>nihil peten. Dom. ad Petitionem Dom.</hi> Wood <hi>admisit, tulit, legit &amp; promulgavit Sententiam predict. sic (ut permittitur) per dict.</hi> Wood <hi>oblat. &amp; porrect. decernendo, pronunci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ando, declarando, adjudicando, restituendo &amp; in Expensis condemnando caeteraque faciendo prout in eadem Sententia plenius continetur, praesenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus tum &amp; ibid.</hi> Adolpho Meetkerk <hi>Coll. novi in Ʋniversitate</hi> Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. <hi>Artis Magistro &amp;</hi> Seymor Tredenham <hi>Collegii omnium animarum in dict. Ʋniversitate Juris Civilis Scholari Testibus ad premissa testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficand. special. rogatis &amp; requisit. in praesentia mei</hi> Johannis Greene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way <hi>Not. Pub. &amp; Reg. assumpti,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>super cujus quidem sententiae prolatione,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Dom.</hi> Wood <hi>requisivit pub. instrument. confici &amp; in actitari.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tunc Dom.</hi> Wood <hi>obtulit Billam expensarum quam petiit admitti &amp; taxari Dominus ad ejus petitionem taxavit eand. ad summam vigin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti Marcarum (factâ prius fide perdict.</hi> Wood <hi>Client. suum exposuisse,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>&amp; expositurum esse summam taxat) &amp; Dom. assignavit pro solu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione dictarum expensarum in vel citra primum diem Mensis</hi> Maij <hi>prox. &amp; judicial. monuit Dominos Doct.</hi> Bury Georg. Verman Ezra Cleeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land Thomam Lethbridge Richardum Hutchins Philippum Thorne Benjam. Archer &amp; Samuel. Adams <hi>dict. sum. taxat, praed. Mro.</hi> Jacobo Colmer <hi>seu ejus procurat. in vel citra diem praed. Tunc Dom.</hi> Wood <hi>petiit sententiam executioni demandari partem{que} suam actual. restitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ere &amp; nomen suum in Libro promptuarii sive Registro dicti Collegii in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribere unde Dominus nomen Mr.</hi> Colmer <hi>inscripsit tum in ea parte Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bri praedict. qua primo deletum sive omissum fuerit tum in ea parte ubi hoc die Nomina sociorum scribuntur &amp; inseruntur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Quae omnia &amp; singula sic (ut permittitur) Coram Nobis Gesta habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta &amp; facta vera esse Paternitati vestrae certificamus eadem{que} unà cum Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teris
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:205037:31"/>vestris Commissionalibus Appellatione Mandato vestro Citatorio Inhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitione cum Monitione pro processu originali nna cum sententia nostra diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitiva praesentibus annex. Clausim &amp; sub Sigillo Vobis transmittimus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>In cujus Rei Testimonium has Literas Testimoniales sive hoc praesens publicum Instrumentum exinde confectum sigillo publico &amp; authentico Officialitatis</hi> Berks <hi>sigillari &amp; communiri &amp; per</hi> Jo. Greeneway <hi>Not. Publ. Actor. nostrorum. in hac parte scribam subsignari &amp; subscribi fecimus Dat. secundo die</hi> Aprilis <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 1690.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Edv. Master <hi>LL. Dre. diocaeseos</hi> Exon <hi>Cancellarius.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <p>
                  <hi>Et ego praefatns</hi> Jo. Greeneway <hi>Regiâ authoritate Not. Publ. Quia pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>missis omnibus &amp; singulis dum sic [ut prefertur) coram Com. praedict agebantur &amp; fiebant praesens personaliter interfui Ea{que} omnia &amp; singula sic fieri, vidi, scivi, audivi &amp; in formam praedict. inactitavi ac man<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> mea propriâ scripsi &amp; redegi Ideo nomen &amp; cognomen meum subscripsi ae signum meum tabellionale solitum &amp; consuetum praesentihus apposui in fidem &amp; Testimonium premissorum ad id specialiter rogatus &amp; requisitus,</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>Ita Testor</hi> Jo. Greeneway <hi>Not. Publ.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </postscript>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <p>
               <hi>These Proceedings being Printed off in hast, the Reader is desired to correct the Lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teral Faults therein; and these Errata in the Defence,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>ERRATA.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>PAge</hi> 5. <hi>Line</hi> 24. <hi>after</hi> therefore <hi>dele</hi> that. <hi>p.</hi> 16. <hi>l,</hi> 11. <hi>dele</hi> are. <hi>p.</hi> 12. <hi>l.</hi> 12 <hi>r.</hi> Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. <hi>p.</hi> 13. <hi>l.</hi> 1. <hi>dele</hi> qui. <hi>l.</hi> 2. <hi>dele</hi> or. <hi>p.</hi> 14. <hi>l.</hi> 6. <hi>r.</hi> provisionary. <hi>l.</hi> 16. declared. <hi>p.</hi> 15 <hi>l.</hi> 1. <hi>r.</hi> alii. <hi>p.</hi> 16. <hi>l.</hi> 2. <hi>r.</hi> Fellows. <hi>l.</hi> 18. <hi>r</hi> propriety.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:205037:31"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>